<chapter id="CPL7_Intro">
<title>CPL7 Introduction</title>

<note><para>
This document discusses the coupler in the CESM1.1 model.
The coupler in this implementation is nearly identical
to the version in the CESM1.0 and CCSM4 release.  In fact, many of the
variables, filenames, comments, and namelists still use the
CCSM name convention.  Any reference in this document to the
CESM1.1 or CESM1 version will generally hold for the CCSM4 release as well.
CESM1.1 differs from CCSM4 and CESM1.0 in one important way, the
runoff model is treated as a separate comoponent in CESM1.1.
CESM1 is used to describe the version of the model in this document.
Where CESM1.0 and CESM1.1 differ, specific versions will be indicated.
</para></note>

<sect1 id="how_to_use">
<title>How to Use This Guide</title>

<para> 
This guide covers the CESM1 top level driver implementation
as well as the coupler component within the system.  The driver
runs on all hardware processors and basically runs the top
level instructions and executes the driver time loop.  The
coupler is a component of the CESM1 system that is run from
within the driver.  It can be run on a subset of the total processors,
and carries out mapping (interpolation), merging, diagnostics,
and other calculations.   The name cpl7 refers to the source
code associated with both the driver and the coupler
parts of the model.  cpl7 code is located in the CESM1 source
tree under models/drv/ and the main program of CESM1 is 
models/drv/driver/ccsm_driver.F90.
</para>
<para>
This document provides a general overview of the cpl7 design.  Then
specific implementation issues are discussed individually.  Finally,
there is a section summarizing all of the cpl7 namelist input.  This
document is written primarily to help users understand the inputs and 
controls within the cpl7 system, but to also provide some background
about the associated implementation.  <ulink url="../coupler_flow.pdf">
Coupler flow diagrams </ulink> are provided in a separate document.
Some additional documentation on
how the coupler works can be found in Craig et al, 
<ulink url="http://hpc.sagepub.com/content/26/1/31">
"A New Flexible Coupler for Earth System Modeling Developed for
CCSM4 and CESM1"</ulink>, International Journal of High Performance Computing Applications 
2012 26: 31 DOI: 10.1177/1094342011428141.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!-- ======================================================================= -->
<chapter id="CPL7_Chapter1">
<title>CPL7 User Guide</title>

<sect1 id="overview">
<title>General Overview</title>

<para>
This document discusses the coupler in the CESM1.1 model.
The coupler in this implementation is nearly identical
to the version in the CESM1.0 and CCSM4 release.  In fact, many of the
variables, filenames, comments, and namelists still use the
CCSM name convention.  Any reference in this document to the
CESM1.1 or CESM1 version will generally hold for the CCSM4 release as well.
CESM1.1 differs from CCSM4 and CESM1.0 in one important way, the
runoff model is treated as a separate comoponent in CESM1.1.
CESM1 is used to describe the version of the model in this document.
Where CESM1.0 and CESM1.1 differ, specific versions will be indicated.
</para>

<para>
Major updates in CESM1.1 compared to CESM1 include
<screen>
- inclusion of a separate runoff component
- ability to run multiple instances of components in a single run
- refactoring of CESM scripts
</screen>
</para>

<para> 
The CESM1 Version of the Community Earth System Model has some
significant changes compared to previous pre-CCSM4 versions.  In particular,
CESM1 is NOT run via multiple executables in a concurrent only
processor layout.  There is
now a top level driver and components are called via standard
init, run, and finalize methods.  Components can be run sequentially,
concurrently, or in some mixed sequential/concurrent layout on processors.  
A coupler component that runs on a subset of the total processors
still exists in the system as part of the driver.  The driver runs
on all processors and the coupler functions (mapping, merging, 
flux calculations, and diagnostics) runs on a user defined subset
of the total processors.  The processor layout is specified at
runtime via namelist inputs.  
</para> 

<para> 
While the processor layout is relatively flexible and components
can be run sequentially or concurrently, the sequencing of the
science in the driver is fixed and independent of the processor
layout.  So changing the processor layout only changes the performance
of the simulation system.  
</para> 

<para> 
Like all components in CESM, the driver scripting system is setup
such that a buildnml (models/drv/bld/cpl.buildnml.csh), a buildexe
(models/drv/bld/cpl.buildexe.csh), and a component template file (models/drv/bld/cpl.template)
are copied or run by the CESM1 scripts.  That script sets up cases
for CESM1.  See the CESM user guide for more detailed information
about this process.  But briefly, the process is as follows,
</para> 

<screen>
 - run create_newcase to generate a case directory.
 - edit env_mach_pes.xml and then run cesm_setup.  this 
   copies the buildnml and buildexe scripts into the case directory and
   generates the .build, .run, and .clean_build scripts.
 - edit env_build.xml and run the .build script.
 - edit env_run.xml and the usr_nl files and submit the .run script.
</screen>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="design">
<title>Design Discussion</title>

<sect2 id="design_overview">
<title>Overview</title>

<para>
In CCSM3/cpl6, all components ran as separate executables and there was no concept of a top-level driver.  
The components started independently and then communicated to the coupler at regular intervals via 
send and receive methods called directly from within each component.  The coupler acted as a central 
hub coordinating data exchange, implicitly managing lags and sequencing, and executing coupler 
operations such as mapping (interpolation) and merging.

</para>
<para>

CESM1/cpl7 is now built as a single executable with a single high-level driver.  The driver runs 
on all processors and handles coupler sequencing, model concurrency, and communication of data 
between components.  The driver calls all model components via common and standard interfaces.  The 
driver also directly calls coupler methods for mapping (interpolation), rearranging, merging, an 
atmosphere/ocean flux calculation, and diagnostics.  In CESM1, the model components and the coupler 
methods can run on subsets of all the processors.  In some sense, the cpl6 sequencing and hub 
attributes have been migrated to the driver level while the cpl6 coupler operations like mapping 
and merging are being done as if a separate coupler component existed in CESM1.  In other words, 
cpl7 consists of a driver that controls the top level sequencing, the processor decomposition, 
and communication between components and the coupler while coupler operations such as 
mapping and merging are running under the driver on a subset of processors as if there were a 
unique coupler model component.

</para>
<para>

CESM1 consists of both data and active components models.  In general, an active component both 
needs data from and provides data to the coupler while data models generally read data from I/O 
and then just provide data to the coupler.  In CESM1, the atmosphere, land, runoff (CESM1.1), and sea 
ice models are always tightly coupled to better resolve the diurnal cycle.  This coupling is 
typically half-hourly, although at higher resolutions, can be more frequent.  The ocean 
model coupling is typically once or a few times per day. The diurnal cycle of ocean surface 
albedo is computed in the coupler for use by the atmosphere model.  The looser ocean coupling 
frequency means the ocean forcing and response is lagged in the system.   There is an option 
in CESM1 to run the ocean tightly coupled without any lags, but this is more often used only when 
running with data ocean components.

</para>
<para>

Depending on the resolution, hardware, run length and physics, a CESM1 run can take several hours 
to several months of wall time to complete.  Runs are typically decades or centuries long, and the 
model typically runs between 1 and 50 model years per wall clock day.  CESM1 has exact restart 
capability and the model is typically run in individual one year or multi-year chunks.  CESM1 has 
automatic resubmission and automatic data archiving capability. 

</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="design_seq">
<title>Sequencing and Concurrency</title>

<para>

In CESM1, the component processor layouts and MPI communicators are derived from namelist input.  
At the present time, there are eight (8) basic processor groups in CESM.  These are associated with the 
atmosphere, land, runoff, ocean, sea ice, land ice, coupler, and global groups, although others could be 
easily added later.  Each of the eight processor groups can be distinct, but that is not a 
requirement of the system.  A user can overlap processor groups relatively arbitrarily.  If all 
processors sets overlap each other in at least one processor, then the model runs sequentially.  
If all processor sets are distinct, the model runs as concurrently as science allows.  
The processor sets for each 
component group are described via 3 basic scalar parameters at the present time; the number of 
mpi tasks, the number of openmp threads per mpi task, and the global mpi task rank of the 
root mpi task for that group.  For example, a layout where the number of mpi tasks is 8, the number 
of threads per mpi task is 4, and the root mpi task is 16 would create a processor group that 
consisted of 32 hardware processors, starting on global mpi task number 16 and it would 
contain 8 mpi tasks.  The global group would have at least 24 tasks and at least 48 hardware
processors.  The driver derives all MPI communicators at initialization and passes 
them to the component models for use.  More information on the coupler concurrency can
be found in the Craig et al IJHPCA 2012 reference mentioned in the top section of this document.

</para>
<para>

As mentioned above, there are two issues related to whether the component models run concurrently.  
The first is whether unique chunks of work are running on distinct processor sets.  The second is 
the sequencing of this work in the driver.  As much as possible, the CESM1 driver sequencing has 
been implemented to maximize the potential amount of concurrency of work between different components.  
Ideally, in a single coupling step, the forcing for all models would be computed first, the models 
could then all run concurrently, and then the driver would advance.  However, scientific 
requirements such as the coordination of surface albedo and atmosphere radiation computations as 
well as general computational stability issues in CESM1 prevents this ideal implementation.  
<link linkend="cpl_fig1">Figure 1</link> 
shows the maximum amount of concurrency supported by the current CESM1 driver implementation 
for a fully active system.  In practice, the scientific constraints mean the active atmosphere 
model cannot run concurrently with the land, runoff, and sea-ice models.  Again, <link linkend="cpl_fig1">
figure 1</link> does not 
necessarily represent the optimum processor layout for performance for any configuration, but it 
provides a practical limit to the amount of concurrency in the system due to scientific constraints. 
With CESM1, results are bit-for-bit identical regardless of the component sequencing because the 
scientific lags are fixed in CESM1 by the implementation, not the processor layout.

</para>

<screenshot>
<screeninfo>CESM Concurrency</screeninfo>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figx1.jpg" format="JPEG"/></imageobject>
<caption>
<para id="cpl_fig1">Figure 1: Maximum potential processor concurrency designed into CESM1
to support scientific requirements and stability.</para>
</caption>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="design_interfaces">
<title>Component Interfaces</title>

<para>

The standard CESM1 component model interfaces are based upon the ESMF design.  Each component 
provides an init, run, and finalize method with consistent arguments.  The CESM1 component interface 
arguments currently consist of Fortran and MCT datatypes, but an alternative ESMF version is also
available.  The physical coupling fields are passed through the interfaces in the init, run, and 
finalize phases.  As part of initialization, an MPI communicator is passed from the driver to 
the component, and grid and decomposition information is passed from the component back to the driver.   
The driver/coupler acquires all information about resolution, configurations, and processor layout 
at run-time from either namelist or from communication with components.

</para>
<para>

Initialization of the system in CESM1 is relatively straight-forward.  First, the eight MPI 
communicators are computed in the driver.  Then the atmosphere, land, runoff, ocean, sea ice, and 
land ice models' initialization methods are called on the appropriate processor sets, and an mpi 
communicator is sent, and the grid and decomposition 
information are passed back to the driver.  Once the driver has all the grid and decomposition 
information from the components, various rearrangers and mappers are initialized that will move 
data between processors, decompositions, and grids as needed at the driver level.  No distinction 
is made in the coupler implementation for sequential versus concurrent execution.  In general, even 
for cases where two components have identical grids and processor layouts, often their decomposition 
is different for performance reasons.  In cases where the grid, decomposition, and processor layout 
are identical between components, the mapping or rearranging operation will degenerate to a local data copy.

</para>
<para>

The interface to the components' run method consists of two distinct bundles of fields.  One is the 
data sent to force the model.  The second is data received from the model for coupling to other 
components.  The run interface also contains a clock that specifies the current time and the run 
length for the model and a data type that encapsulates grid, decomposition, and scalar coupling 
information.  These interfaces generally follow the ESMF design principles, and there are alternative
ESMF interfaces supported in the CESM1 components.

</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="design_mct">
<title>MCT, The Model Coupling Toolkit</title>

<para>

MCT was a critical piece of software in the CCSM3 cpl6 coupler.  In the updated CESM1 cpl7 coupler, 
the MCT attribute_vector, global_segmap, and general_grid datatypes have been adopted at the highest 
levels of the driver, and they are used directly in the component init, run, and finalize interfaces.  
In addition, MCT is used for all data rearranging and mapping (interpolation). The clock used by CESM1 
at the driver level is based on the ESMF specification.  Mapping weights are still generated off-line 
using the SCRIP or ESMF packages as a preprocessing step.  They are read into CESM1 using a 
subroutine that reads and distributes the mapping weights in reasonably small chunks to minimize the 
memory footprint.  Development of the CESM1 cpl7 coupler not only relies on MCT, but MCT developers 
contributed significantly to the design and implementation of the cpl7 driver.   Development of both 
the cpl6 and cpl7 coupler has resulted from a particularly strong and close collaboration between 
NCAR and the Department of Energy Argonne National Lab.

</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="design_perf">
<title>Memory, Parallel IO, and Performance</title>

<para>

CESM1 is targeting much higher resolutions than any previous CCSM coupled model.  In order to facilitate 
scientific climate model exploration and development at these scales, the technology had to be put in 
place first to enable testing of this case.  Efforts have been made to reduce the memory footprint and improve 
memory scaling in all components with a target of being able to run the fully coupled system at one 
tenth (0.1) degree resolution globally on tens-of-thousands of processors with each processor having 
as little as 512 Mb of memory.  This target limits the number of global arrays that can be allocated 
on any processor to just a few, at most, at any time. The memory limitations have imposed new 
constraints on component model initialization, and significant refactoring has been required in 
some models' initialitialization to reduce the amount of global memory used.  In addition, all components 
now use PIO, a parallel IO library, to minimize the memory used during IO and to provide a
flexible path towards improved IO performance through pnetcdf or other parallel IO implementations.
PIO has allowed testing of CESM1 at high resolutions that were previously memory limited in 
part because of IO.

</para>
<para>

Scaling to tens-of-thousands of processors requires reasonable performance scaling of the models, 
and all components have worked at improving scaling via changes to algorithms, infrastructure, or 
decompositions.  In particular, decompositions using shared memory blocking, space filling 
curves, and all three spatial dimensions have been implemented to varying degrees in all 
components to increase parallelization and improve scalability.  The Craig et al IJHPCA 2012
reference mentioned in the first section of this document provides a summary of
scaling performance of the CESM1 coupler for several coupler kernals.

</para>
<para>

In practice, CESM1 performance, load balance, and scalability are limited as a result of the size, 
complexity, and multiple model character of the system. Within the system, each component has its own 
scaling characteristics.  In particular, each may have processor count "sweet-spots" where the 
individual component model performs particularly well.  This might occur within a component because 
of internal load balance, decomposition capabilities, communication patterns, or cache usage.  
Second, component performance can vary over the length of the model run.  This occurs because of 
seasonal variability of the cost of physics in models, changes in performance during an 
adjustment (spin-up) phase, and temporal variability in calling certain model operations like 
radiation, dynamics, or I/O. Third, the hardware or batch queueing system might have some constraints 
on the total number of processors that are available.  For instance, on 16 or 32 way shared memory 
node, a user is typically charged based on node usage, not processor usage.  So there is no cost 
savings running on 40 processors versus 64 processors on a 32-way node system.  As a result of all 
of these issues, load-balancing CESM1 perfectly is generally not possible.  But to a large degree, 
if one accepts the limitations, a load balance configuration with acceptable idle-time and reasonably 
good throughput is nearly always possible to configure.  

</para>
<para>

Load-balancing CESM1 requires a number of considerations such as which components are run, their absolute resolution, and their relative resolution; cost, scaling and processor count sweet-spots for each component; and internal load imbalance within a component. It is often best to load balance the system with all significant run-time I/O turned off because this generally occurs very infrequently (typically one timestep per month in CESM1), is best treated as a separate cost, and can bias interpretation of the overall model load balance. Also, the use of OpenMP threading in some or all of the system is dependent on the hardware/OS support as well as whether the system supports running all MPI and mixed MPI/OpenMP on overlapping processors for different components.  Finally, should the components run sequentially, concurrently, or some combination of the two.  Typically, a series of short test runs is done with the desired production configuration to establish a reasonable load balance setup for the production job.  CESM1 provides some post-run analysis of the performance and load balance of the system to assist users in improving the processor layouts.

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>

