<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="definitions_variables.xsl" ?>

<definitions_variables> 

  <entry id="DOUT_S"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>TRUE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Logical to turn on short term archiving.
    If TRUE, short term archiving will be turned on.</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DOUT_S_SAVE_INTERIM_RESTART_FILES"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>FALSE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Logical to archive all interim restart files, not just those at eor
    If TRUE, perform short term archiving on all interim restart files,
    not just those at the end of the run. By default, this value is FALSE.
    The restart files are saved under the specific component directory
    ($DOUT_S_ROOT/$CASE/$COMPONENT/rest rather than the top-level $DOUT_S_ROOT/$CASE/rest directory).
    Interim restart files are created using the REST_N and REST_OPTION variables.
    This is for expert users ONLY and requires expert knowledge. 
    We will not document this further in this guide.</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_S_SAVE_EVERY_NTH_RESTART_FILE_SET"> 
    <type>integer</type>
    <value>0</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Save every Nth set of restart files and delete all others
      If value is greater than 0, then only save the nth restart set in the $DOUT_S_ROOT/$CASE/rest location. 
      Always preserve the most recent restart set regardless.</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_S_SAVE_ALL_ON_DISK"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>TRUE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>logical to save contents of the short term archive on disk
      If TRUE, create hardlinks from the short term archive $DOUT_S_ROOT.locked/$CASE
      directory to the $DOUT_S_ROOT/$CASE directory.</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_S_GENERATE_TSERIES"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>FALSE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Logical to generate time-series files from the history time-slice files
    If TRUE, create the single variable time series files using the history time slice files.
    All the time invariant metadata is included in each variable time series file header. 
    Rules for how the tseries files are created are specified in the env_archive.xml file.</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_S_SAVE_HISTORY_FILES"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>FALSE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Logical to save history time slice files after the variable time series have been generated
    If TRUE, none of the history time slice files will be deleted from the $DOUT_S_ROOT/$CASE location after the
    variable time series files are successfully generated. *WARNING* setting this option to TRUE can
    more than double the disk space used by the output data for a given job.</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_L_MS"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>FALSE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>If TRUE, perform long-term archiving on the output data.
      logical to turn on long term archiving (if DOUT_S is also TRUE)</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DOUT_L_HPSS_ACCNT">
    <type>char</type>
    <value>00000000</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc></desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="DOUT_L_HTAR"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>FALSE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>If true, DOUT_L_HTAR the long-term archiver will store history data in annual tar files. 
    Not currently implemented</desc>
  </entry> 

  <entry id="DOUT_L_SAVE_ALL_ON_DISK"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <value>TRUE</value>
    <group>run_data_archive</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Save contents of short term archive on disk after the long term archiver has successfully completed
    If TRUE, this keeps the output data in DOUT_S_ROOT on disk after the long term (lt_archive.sh) archiver is run.</desc>
  </entry> 

</definitions_variables> 
