<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="namelist_definition.xsl"?>

<namelist_definition>

<!-- ========================================================================================  -->
<!-- DICE Namelists                                                                            -->
<!-- ========================================================================================  -->

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- shr_strmdata_nml (file dice_ice_in)       -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="datamode" 
type="char*256"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="NULL,SSTDATA,COPYALL">
general method that operates on the data.  this is generally
implemented in the data models but is set in the strdata method for
convenience.  valid options are dependent on the data model and will
be described elsewhere.  NULL is always a valid option and means no
data will be generated.  default='NULL'
  datamode = "NULL"
Turns off the data model as a provider of data to the coupler.  The
ice_present flag will be set to false and the coupler will assume no
exchange of data to or from the data model.
  dataMode = "COPYALL"
Copies all fields directly from the input data streams Any required
fields not found on an input stream will be set to zero.
  dataMode = "SSTDATA"
Is a prognostic mode. It requires data be sent to the ice
model. Ice fraction (extent) data is read from an input stream,
atmosphere state variables are received from the coupler, and then
an atmosphere-ice surface flux is computed and sent to the
coupler. It is called "SSTDATA" mode because normally the ice
fraction data is found in the same data files that provide SST
data to the data ocean model. They are normally found in the same
file because the SST and ice fraction data are derived from the
same observational data sets and are consistent with each other.
  Set by the xml variable DICE_MODE in env_run.xml
  Currently, DICE_MODE can be [ssmi, ssmi_iaf, null] 
If DICE_MODE is set to ssmi or ssmi_iaf, datamode will be set to SSTDATA
If DICE_MODE is set to null, datamodel will be set to NULL   
</entry>

<entry id="domainfile" 
type="char*256" 
category="streams"
input_pathname="abs" 
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
spatial gridfile associated with the strdata.  grid information will
be read from this file and that grid will serve as the target grid
for all input data for this strdata input.  
</entry>

<entry id="fillalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"
valid_values="copy,bilinear,nn,nnoni,nnonj,spval">
array (up to 30 elements) of fill algorithms associated with the array
of streams.  valid options are just copy (ie. no fill), special value,
nearest neighbor, nearest neighbor in "i" direction, or nearest
neighbor in "j" direction.
valid values:  'copy','spval','nn','nnoni','nnonj'  
default: "nn".
</entry>

<entry id="fillmask"
type="char*256(30)"
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask">
plays no role is fill algorithm at the present time.  
valid values: "nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask"
default: "nomask"
</entry>

<entry id="fillread" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to read in instead of computing the
weights on the fly for the fill operation.  if this is set, fillalgo
and fillmask are ignored.
default: unset
</entry>

<entry id="fillwrite" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml">
array (up to 30 elements)  of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to generate after weights are
computed on the fly for the fill operation.  this allows a user to
save and reuse a set of weights later.  
default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="mapmask" 
type="char*256(30)"
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"
valid_values="nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask">
array (up to 30 elements) of masking algorithms for mapping input data
associated with the array of streams.  valid options are map only from
valid src points, map only to valid destination points, ignore all
masks, map only from valid src points to valid destination points.
valid values: srcmask, dstmask, nomask,bothmask
default: dstmask
</entry>

<entry id="mapalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="copy,bilinear,nn,nnoni,nnonj,spval">
array (up to 30 elements) of fill algorithms associated with the array
of streams.  valid options are copy by index, set to special value,
nearest neighbor, nearest neighbor in "i" direction, nearest neighbor
in "j" direction, or bilinear.  
valid values: copy,spval,nn,nnoni,nnonj,bilinear
default: bilinear
</entry>

<entry id="mapread" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"> 
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to read instead of computing
weights on the fly for the mapping (interpolation) operation.  if this
is set, mapalgo and mapmask are ignored.  default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="mapwrite" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to generate after weights are
computed on the fly for the mapping (interpolation) operation.  this
allows a user to save and reuse a set of weights later.
default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="tintalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="coszen,nearest,linear,lower,upper">
array (up to 30 elements) of time interpolation options associated with the array of
streams.  
valid values: lower,upper,nearest,linear,coszen
  lower   = Use lower time-value
  upper   = Use upper time-value
  nearest = Use the nearest time-value
  linear  = Linearly interpolate between the two time-values
  coszen  = Scale according to the cosine of the solar zenith angle (for solar)
default="linear".
</entry>

<entry id="taxmode" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="extend,cycle,limit">
array of time axis modes associated with the array of streams for
handling data outside the specified stream time axis.  
valid options are to cycle the data based on the first, last, and
align settings associated with the stream dataset, to extend the first
and last valid value indefinitely, or to limit the interpolated data
to fall only between the least and greatest valid value of the time array.
valid values: cycle,extend,limit
    extend = extrapolate before and after the period by using the first or last value.
    cycle  = cycle between the range of data
    limit  = restrict to the period for which the data is valid
default="cycle".
</entry>

<entry id="dtlimit" 
type="real(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of delta time ratio limits placed on the
time interpolation associated with the array of streams.  this real
value causes the model to stop if the ratio of the running maximum
delta time divided by the minimum delta time is greater than the
dtlimit for that stream.  for instance, with daily data, the delta
time should be exactly one day throughout the dataset and the computed
maximum divided by minimum delta time should always be 1.0.  for
monthly data, the delta time should be between 28 and 31 days and the
maximum ratio should be about 1.1.  the running value of the delta
time is computed as data is read and any wraparound or cycling is also
included.  this input helps trap missing data or errors in cycling.
to turn off trapping, set the value to 1.0e30 or something similar.
default=1.5. 
</entry>

<entry id="streams" 
type="char*256(30)" 
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
character array (up to 30 elements) of stream input files.  this
string is actually parsed by a stream method and so the format is
specified by the stream module.  this string consists of a
"stream_input_filename year_align year_first year_last".  the
stream_input_filename is a stream text input file and the format and
options are described elsewhere.  year_align, year_first, and
year_last provide information about the time axis of the file and how
to relate the input time axis to the model time axis.  
default="null".
</entry>

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- dice_nml (in file dice_in)                -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="ice_in" 
type="char*256" 
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" 
valid_values="">
The data ice specific namelist input is as follows.  The namelist
input filename is hardwired in the data model code to "dice_in".  The
namelist group is called "dice_nml".  The variable formats are
character string (char), integer (int), double precision real (r8), or
logical (log) or one dimensional arrays of any of those things. 
ice_in sets the filename for the data ice shr_strmdata namelist.  
default: dice_ice_in.
</entry>

<entry id="decomp" 
type="char*4" 
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" 
valid_values="1d,root" >
set the decomposition option for the data model.  valid options are
placing the global array on the root task or a simple stride-one
load balanced one-dimensional decomposition.  other decompositions
may be added in the future.  
valid values are ['root','1d'].
  1d   = Vector decomposition
  root = run only on the master task
default='1d'. 
</entry>

<entry id="flux_qacc" 
type="logical"  
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" >
activates water accumulation/melt wrt Q
default: .false.
</entry>

<entry id="flux_qacc0" 
type="logical"  
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" >
initial water accumulation value
default: 0.
</entry>

<entry id="flux_qmin" 
type="logical"  
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" >
bound on melt rate
default: -300.0e0
</entry>

<entry id="flux_swpf" 
type="logical"  
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" >
short-wave penatration factor
default: 0.
</entry>

<entry id="restfilm" 
type="char*256" 
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" 
valid_values="">
Model restart filename for the data ice model data.  This is optional.
If both restfils and restfilm are undefined, the restart filename will
be read from the ICE restart pointer file (or files for multiple instances).  
default='undefined'.
</entry>

<entry id="restfils" 
type="char*256" 
category="dice"
group="dice_nml" 
valid_values="">
Stream restart filename for the data ice stream data.  This is
optional.  If both restfils and restfilm are undefined, the restart
filename will be read from the DICE restart pointer file (or files for
multiple instances).  
default: 'undefined'
</entry>

<entry id="force_prognostic_true"
type="logical" 
category="dice"
group="dice_nml">
If TRUE, prognostic is forced to true.
default=false 
</entry>

<entry id="logfile" 
type="char*256" 
category="dice"
group="modelio" 
valid_values="">
DICE logfile name
default: 'ice.log'
</entry>


</namelist_definition>
