<!-- Beg of tools chapter -->
<chapter id="tools">
<title>Using the &clm; tools to create your own input datasets</title>
<para>
There are several tools provided with &clm; that allow you to create your own input 
datasets at resolutions you choose, or to interpolate initial conditions to a different
resolution, or used to compare &clm; history files between different cases. The tools are
all available in the <filename>models/lnd/clm/tools</filename> directory. Most of the tools
are &FORTRAN; stand-alone programs in their own directory, but there is also a suite of
&ncl;
scripts in the <filename>ncl_scripts</filename> directory. Some of the &ncl; scripts are
very specialized and not meant for general use, and we won't document them here. They
still contain documentation in the script itself and the README file in the tools
directory. But, the list of generally important scripts and programs are:
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>cprnc</emphasis> to compare &netcdf; files with a time axis.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>interpinic</emphasis> to interpolate initial condition files.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>mkgriddata</emphasis> to create grid datasets.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>mkdatadomain</emphasis> to create domain files from grid datasets
used by &datm; or <acronym>docn</acronym>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>mksurfdata</emphasis> to create surface datasets from grid datasets.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>ncl_scripts/getregional_datasets.pl</emphasis> script to extract a
region or a single-point from global input datasets. See the single-point chapter
for more information on this.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>ncl_scripts/npdepregrid.ncl</emphasis> interpolate the Nitrogen
deposition datasets to a new resolution.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para> <emphasis>ncl_scripts/aerdepregrid.ncl</emphasis> interpolate the Aerosol
deposition datasets to a new resolution.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
In the sections to come we will go into detailed description of how to use each of
these tools in turn. First, however we will discuss the common environment variables
and options that are used by all of the &FORTRAN; tools. Second, we go over the outline
of the entire file creation process for all input files needed by &clm; for a new 
resolution, then we turn to each tool. In the last section we will
discuss how to customize files for particular observational sites.
</para>

<sect1 id="tool_build">
<title>Common environment variables and options used in building the &FORTRAN;
tools</title>
<para>
The &FORTRAN; tools all have similar makefiles, and similar options for building.
All of the Makefiles use GNU Make extensions and thus require that you use GNU make
to use them. They also auto detect the type of platform you are on, using "uname -s"
and set the compiler, compiler flags and such accordingly. There are also environment
variables that can be set to set things that must be customized. All the tools use
&netcdf; and hence require the path to the &netcdf; libraries and include files.
On some platforms (such as Linux) multiple compilers can be used, and hence there
are env variables that can be set to change the &FORTRAN; and/or "C" compilers used.
The tools other than <command>cprnc</command> also allow finer control, by also 
allowing the user to add compiler flags they choose, for both &FORTRAN; and "C", as 
well as picking the compiler, linker and and add linker options. Finally the tools 
other than <command>cprnc</command> allow you to turn
optimization on (which is off by default  but on for the <command>mksurfdata</command> and
<command>interpinic</command>
programs) with the <envar>OPT</envar> flag so that the 
tool will run faster. To get even faster performance, the <command>interpinic</command>,
<command>mksurfdata</command>, and
<command>mkgriddata</command> programs allow you to also use the <envar>SMP</envar> to 
turn on multiple shared memory processors.
When <envar>SMP=TRUE</envar> you set the number of threads used by the program with
the <envar>OMP_NUM_THREADS</envar> environment variable.
</para>
<para>
Options used by all: <command>cprnc</command>, <command>interpinic</command>,
<command>mkdatadomain</command>, <command>mkgriddata</command>, and 
<command>mksurfdata</command>
<simplelist>
<member><envar>LIB_NETCDF</envar> -- sets the location of the &netcdf; library.</member>
<member><envar>INC_NETCDF</envar> -- sets the location of the &netcdf; include files.</member>
<member><envar>USER_FC</envar> -- sets the name of the &FORTRAN; compiler.</member>
</simplelist>
Options used by: <command>interpinic</command>, <command>mkdatadomain</command>,
<command>mkgriddata</command>, and <command>mksurfdata</command>
<simplelist>
<member><envar>MOD_NETCDF</envar> -- sets the location of the &netcdf; &FORTRAN; module.</member>
<member><envar>USER_LINKER</envar> -- sets the name of the linker to use.</member>
<member><envar>USER_CPPDEFS</envar> -- adds any CPP defines to use.</member>
<member><envar>USER_CFLAGS</envar> -- add any "C" compiler flags to use.</member>
<member><envar>USER_FFLAGS</envar> -- add any &FORTRAN; compiler flags to use.</member>
<member><envar>USER_LDFLAGS</envar> -- add any linker flags to use.</member>
<member><envar>USER_CC</envar> -- sets the name of the "C" compiler to use.</member>
<member><envar>OPT</envar> -- set to TRUE to compile the code optimized (TRUE or FALSE)</member>
</simplelist>
Options used by: interpinic, mkgriddata, and mksurfdata:
<simplelist>
<member><envar>SMP</envar> -- set to TRUE to turn on shared memory parallelism (i.e.
&omp;) (TRUE or FALSE)</member>
<member><filename>Filepath</filename> -- list of directories to build source code from.</member>
<member><filename>Srcfiles</filename> -- list of source code filenames to build executable from.</member>
</simplelist>
Options used only by cprnc:
<simplelist>
<member><envar>EXEDIR</envar> -- sets the location where the executable will be built.</member>
<member><envar>VPATH</envar> -- colon delimited path list to find the source files.</member>
</simplelist>
More details on each environment variable.
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><envar>LIB_NETCDF</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the path to the &netcdf; library file 
(<filename>libnetcdf.a</filename>). If not 
set it defaults to <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename>. In order to use the tools
you need to build the &netcdf; library and be able to link to it. In order to build
the model with a particular compiler you may have to compile the &netcdf; library with
the same compiler (or at least a compatible one).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>INC_NETCDF</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the path to the &netcdf; include directory (in order to find
the include file <filename>netcdf.inc</filename>).
if not set it defaults to <filename>/usr/local/include</filename>.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>MOD_NETCDF</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the path to the &netcdf; module directory (in order to find
the &netcdf; &FORTRAN90; module file when &netcdf; is used with a &FORTRAN90;
<command>use statement</command>. When not set it defaults to the 
<envar>LIB_NETCDF</envar> value.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_FC</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the command name to the &FORTRAN90; compiler to use when
compiling the tool. The default compiler to use depends on the platform. And
for example, on the AIX platform this variable is NOT used
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_LINKER</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the command name to the linker to use when linking the object
files from the compiler together to build the executable. By default this is set to
the value of the &FORTRAN90; compiler used to compile the source code.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_CPPDEFS</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable adds additional optional values to define for the C preprocessor.
Normally, there is no reason to do this as there are very few CPP tokens in the CLM
tools. However, if you modify the tools there may be a reason to define new CPP
tokens.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_CC</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable sets the command name to the "C" compiler to use when
compiling the tool. The default compiler to use depends on the platform. And
for example, on the AIX platform this variable is NOT used
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_CFLAGS</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable adds additional compiler options for the "C" compiler to use
when compiling the tool. By default the compiler options are picked according
to the platform and compiler that will be used.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_FFLAGS</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable adds additional compiler options for the &FORTRAN90; compiler to use
when compiling the tool. By default the compiler options are picked according
to the platform and compiler that will be used.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>USER_LDFLAGS</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable adds additional options to the linker that will be used when linking
the object files into the executable. By default the linker options are picked according
to the platform and compiler that is used.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>SMP</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable flags if shared memory parallelism (using i&omp;) should be used when 
compiling the tool.  It can be set to either <literal>TRUE</literal> or 
<literal>FALSE</literal>, by default it is set to <literal>FALSE</literal>, so 
shared memory parallelism is NOT used. When set to <literal>TRUE</literal> you can
set the number of threads by using the <envar>OMP_NUM_THREADS</envar> environment
variable. Normally, the most you would set this to would be to the number of on-node
CPU processors. Turning this on should make the tool run much faster.
</para>
<caution>
<para>
Note, that depending on the compiler answers may be different when <envar>SMP</envar>
is activated.
</para>
</caution>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><envar>OPT</envar></term><listitem> 
<para>
This variable flags if compiler optimization should be used when 
compiling the tool.  It can be set to either <literal>TRUE</literal> or 
<literal>FALSE</literal>, by default it is set to <literal>FALSE</literal> for
<command>mkdatadomain</command> and <literal>TRUE</literal> for
<command>mksurfdata</command> and <command>interpinic</command>.
Turning this on should make the tool run much faster.
</para>
<caution>
<para>
Note, you should expect that answers will be different when <envar>OPT</envar>
is activated.
</para>
</caution>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><filename>Filepath</filename></term><listitem> 
<para>
All of the tools are stand-alone and don't  need any outside code to operate. The
<filename>Filepath</filename> is the list of directories needed to compile
and hence is always simply "." the current directory. Several tools use
copies of code outside their directory that is in the &cesm;
distribution (either csm_share code or &clm; source code).
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><filename>Srcfiles</filename></term><listitem> 
<para>
The <filename>Srcfiles</filename> lists the filenames of the source code to use
when building the tool.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><filename>EXEDIR</filename></term><listitem> 
<para>
The <command>cprnc</command> tool uses this variable to set the location of where the executable
will be built. The default is the current directory.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><filename>VPATH</filename></term><listitem> 
<para>
The <command>cprnc</command> tool uses this variable to set the colon delimited pathnames of where
the source code exists.  The default is the current directory.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</para>

<note>
<para>
There are several files that are copies of the original files from either
<filename>models/lnd/clm/src/main</filename>, 
<filename>models/csm_share/shr</filename>, or copies from other tool
directories. By having copies the tools can all be made stand-alone, but
any changes to the originals will have to be put into the tool directories
as well.
</para>
</note>

<para>The <emphasis>README.filecopies</emphasis> (which can be found in
<filename>models/lnd/clm/tools)</filename> is repeated here.</para>
<programlisting width="99">
&filecopies;
</programlisting>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tool_run">
<title>General information on running the &FORTRAN; tools</title>
<para>
The tools run either one of two ways, with a namelist to provide options, or
with command line arguments (and NOT both). <command>interpinic</command> and
<command>cprnc</command> run with command line arguments, and the other tools
run with namelists.
</para>
<sect2 id="tool_run_namelist">
<title>Running &FORTRAN; tools with namelists</title>
<para>
<command>mkgridata</command>, <command>mksurfdata</command> and 
<command>mkdatadomain</command> run with namelists that are read from
standard input. Hence, you create a namelist and then run them by
redirecting the namelist file into standard input as follows:
<screen width="99">
./program &lt; namelist
</screen>
For programs with namelists there is at least one sample namelist with the
name "program".namelist (i.e. <filename>mksurfdata.namelist</filename> 
for the <command>mksurfdata</command> program). There may also be other sample
namelists that end in a different name besides "namelist". Namelists that you create 
should be similar to the example namelist. The namelist values are also documented 
along with the other namelists in the:
<ulink url="../../bld/namelist_files/namelist_definition.xml">
<filename>models/lnd/clm/bld/namelist_files/namelist_definition.xml</filename></ulink>
file and default values in the:
<ulink url="../../bld/namelist_files/namelist_defaults_clm_tools.xml">
<filename>models/lnd/clm/bld/namelist_files/namelist_defaults_clm_tools.xml</filename></ulink>
file.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="tool_run_commandline">
<title>Running &FORTRAN; tools with command line options</title>
<para>
<command>interpinic</command> and <command>cprnc</command> run with command line
arguments. The detailed sections below will give you more information on the command
line arguments specific to each tool. Also running the tool without any arguments
will give you a general synopsis on how to run the tool. For example to get help
on running <command>interpinic</command> do the following.
<screen width="99">
cd models/lnd/clm/tools/interpinic
gmake
./interpinic
</screen>
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="tool_run_smp">
<title>Running &FORTRAN; tools built with SMP=TRUE</title>
<para>
When you enable <envar>SMP=TRUE</envar> on your build of one of the tools that
make use of it, you are using &omp; for shared memory parallelism (SMP). In
SMP loops are run in parallel with different threads run on different processors
all of which access the same memory (called on-node). Thus you can only usefully 
run up to the number of processors that are available on a single-node of the machine
you are running on. For example, on the &ncar; machine bluefire there are 32 processors
per node, but the SMT hardware on the machine allows you to submit twice as many 
threads or 64 threads. So to run the <command>mksurfdata</command> on bluefire 
optimized, with 64 threads you would do the following:
<screen width="99">
cd models/lnd/clm/tools/mksurfdata
gmake OPT=TRUE SMP=TRUE
setenv OMP_NUM_THREADS 64
./mksurfdata &lt; mksurfdata.namelist
</screen>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="file_creation_process">
<title>The File Creation Process</title>

<para>
When just creating a replacement file for an existing one, the relevant tool should
be used directly to create the file. When you are creating a set of files for a new
resolution there are some dependencies between the tools that you need to keep in mind
when creating them. The main dependency is that the <command>mkgriddata</command> MUST
be done first as the grid dataset is then input into the other tools. Also look at
<xref linkend="table_required_files"></xref>.
</para>

<procedure>
<title>Creating a complete set of files for input to &clm;</title>
<step>
<title>Create grid and fraction datasets</title>
<para>
First use <command>mkgriddata</command> to create grid and fraction datasets.
See <xref linkend="mkgriddata"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Create domain dataset (if NOT already done)</title>
<para>
Next use <command>mkdatadomain</command> to create a domain file for use by
&datm; from the grid and fraction datasets just created. This is required, unless
a domain file already created was input into <command>mkgriddata</command> on
the previous step.
See <xref linkend="mkdatadomain"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step>
<title>Create surface datasets</title>
<para>
Next use <command>mksurfdata</command> to create a surface dataset, using the grid
dataset as input.
See <xref linkend="mksurfdata"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Interpolate  aerosol deposition datasets (optional)</title>
<para>
By default the atmosphere model will interpolate
these datasets on the fly, so you don't normally need to do this step.
A reason you might want to do this is to make the read and interpolation faster,
by reducing the amount of data read in and removing the need for the interpolation.
So, if you do, you can use <command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command> to regrid aerosol 
deposition datasets to your new resolution using the grid dataset as input.
See <xref linkend="aerdepregrid"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Interpolate Nitrogen deposition datasets (optional, but only needed if running &clmcn;)</title>
<para>
By default Nitrogen deposition is read in from stream
files at 2-degree resolution and interpolated to the resolution you are running at,
so you don't need to do this step.  As with aerosol deposition datasets a reason
you might want to do this is to make the read and interpolation faster,
by reducing the amount of data read in and removing the need for the interpolation.
So, if you do you can use <command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> 
to regrid Nitrogen deposition datasets to your new resolution using the grid dataset 
as input.
See <xref linkend="ndepregrid"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step>
<title>Create some sort of initial condition dataset</title>

<para>
You then need to do one of the following three options to have an initial dataset
to start from.
</para>

<substeps>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Use spinup-procedures to create initial condition datasets</title>
<para>
The first option is to do the spinup procedures from arbitrary initial conditions
to get good initial datasets. This is the most robust method to use.
See <xref linkend="CLMSP_SPINUP"></xref>, <xref linkend="CN_SPINUP"></xref>, or 
<xref linkend="CNDV_SPINUP"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Use <command>interpinic</command> to interpolate existing initial
condition datasets</title>
<para>
The next option is to interpolate from spunup datasets at a different resolution, using
<command>interpinic</command>.
See <xref linkend="interpinic"></xref> for more information on this.
</para>
</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Start up from arbitrary initial conditions</title>
<para>
The last alternative is to run from arbitrary initial conditions without using any
spun-up datasets. This is inappropriate when using &clmcn; (bgc=cn or cndv) as it 
takes a long time to spinup Carbon pools. 
<warning>
<para>
This is NOT recommended as many fields in &clm; take a long time to equilibrate.
</para>
</warning>
</para>
</step>

</substeps>

</step>

<step performance="optional">
<title>Enter the new datasets into the &buildnml; XML database</title>
<para>
The last optional thing to do is to enter the new datasets into the &buildnml;
XML database. See <xref linkend="adding_files"></xref> for more information on
doing this. This is optional because the user may enter these files into their
namelists manually. The advantage of entering them into the database is so that
they automatically come up when you create new cases.
</para>
</step>

</procedure>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="cprnc">
<title>Using the <command>cprnc</command> tool to compare two history files</title>
<para>
<command>cprnc</command> is a tool shared by both <acronym>CAM</acronym> and &clm; to compare two
&netcdf; history files.
It differences every field that has a time-axis that is also shared on both files,
and reports a summary of the difference. The summary includes the three largest 
differences, as well as the root mean square (RMS) difference. It also gives some
summary information on the field as well. You have to enter at least one file, and up to
two files. With one file it gives you summary information on the file, and with two it
gives you information on the differences between the two. At the end it will give you a
summary of the fields compared and how many fields were different and how many were
identical.
</para>
<para>
Options:
<simplelist>
<member>-m = do NOT align time-stamps before comparing</member>
<member>-v = verbose output</member>
<member>-ipr</member>
<member>-jpr</member>
<member>-kpr</member>
</simplelist>
See the <command>cprnc</command>
<ulink url="../../tools/cprnc/README">README</ulink> file for more details which is
repeated here:
<screen width="99">
&cprnc_readme;
</screen>
<note>
<para>
To compare files with OUT a time axis you can use the <command>cprnc.ncl</command>
&ncl; script in <filename>models/lnd/clm/tools/ncl_scripts</filename>. It won't give
you the details on the differences but will report if the files are identical or 
different.
</para>
</note>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="interpinic">
<title>Using <command>interpinic</command> to interpolate initial conditions to different
resolutions</title>
<para>
"interpinic" is used to interpolate initial conditions from one resolution to another.
In order to do the interpolation you must first run &clm; to create a restart file to
use as the "template" to interpolate into. Running from arbitrary initial conditions
(i.e. finidat = ' ') for a single time-step is sufficient to do this. Make sure the
model produces a restart file. You also need to make sure that you setup the same
configuration that you want to run the model with, when you create the template file.
</para>
<para>
Command line options to <command>interpinic</command>:
<simplelist>
<member>-i = Input filename to interpolate from</member>
<member>-o = Output interpolated file, and starting template file</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
<para>
There is a sample template file in the <filename>models/lnd/clm/tools/interpinic</filename>
directory and can be used to run interpolate to.
However, this file was created with an older version of &clm; and hence
we actually recommend that you would do a short run with &clm; to create a template file
to use.
</para>
<para>

<example id="example_createtemplate">
<title>Example of running &clm; to create a template file for
<command>interpinic</command> to interpolate to</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd scripts
> ./create_newcase -case cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN -res f10_f10 -compset I1850CN \
-mach bluefire
> cd cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN
# Set starting date to end of year
> ./xmlchange -file env_conf.xml -id RUN_STARTDATE -val 1948-12-31
# Set year align to starting year
> ./xmlchange -file env_conf.xml -id DATM_CLMNCEP_YR_ALIGN -val 1948
# Set to run a cold start
> ./xmlchange -file env_conf.xml -id CLM_FORCE_COLDSTART -val on
# Set to run only a single day, so a restart file will be created on Jan/1/1949
> ./xmlchange -file env_run.xml -id STOP_N -val 1
# Then configure, build and run as normal
> ./configure -case
> ./cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN.bluefire.build
> ./cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN.bluefire.submit
# And copy the resulting restart file to your interpinic directory
> cd ../models/lnd/clm/tools/interpinic
> cp /ptmp/$LOGIN/cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN/run/cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN.clm2.r.1949-01-01-00000.nc .
</screen>
</example>
</para>
<para>
In the next example we build <command>interpinic</command> optimized with shared
memory on for 64 threads so that it runs as fast as possible, to interpolate one of
the standard 1-degree datasets to the above 10x15 template file that we created.
</para>
<example id="example_interpinic">
<title>Example of building and running <command>interpinic</command> to 
interpolate a 1-degree <filename>finidat</filename> dataset to 10x15</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/tools/interpinic
> gmake OPT=TRUE SMP=TRUE
> env OMP_NUM_THREADS=64 ./interpinic -o cr_f10_TmpltI1850CN.clm2.r.1949-01-01-00000.nc /
-i /fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/ccsm4_init/b40.1850.track1.1deg.006/0863-01-01/b40.1850.track1.1deg.006.clm2.r.0863-01-01-00000.nc
</screen>
<para>
<tip>
<para>
Running <command>interpinic</command> at high resolution can take a long time, so we
recommend that you always build it optimized and with shared memory processing on, to
cut down the run time as much as possible.
</para>
</tip>
<warning>
<para>
<command>interpinic</command> does NOT work for CNDV (bgc=cndv).
</para>
</warning>
</para>
</example>

<para>
In <xref linkend="runinit_ibm.csh"></xref> we give a simpler way to run
<command>interpinic</command> for several standard resolutions at once, with a script
to loop over several resolutions. This is useful for &clm; developers who need to
create many <filename>finidat</filename> files at once.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="mkgriddata">
<title>Using <command>mkgriddata</command> to create grid datasets</title>
<para>
<command>mkgriddata</command> is used to create grid, fraction, and topography 
datasets to run &clm; at a new resolution. It is typically the first step in creating 
datasets needed to run &clm; at a new resolution (followed by 
<command>mksurfdata</command>, and 
then the interpolation programs, <command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command>, and 
<command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> when running with CN).
</para>

<sect2 id="mkgriddata_nml">
<title>mkgriddata namelist</title>
<para>
<command>mkgriddata</command> is controlled by a namelist. There are ten different
namelist items, and you need to use enough of them so that files will be output.
The different types of input datasets contain different input data types, that
correspond to the three different types of output files: grid, fraction, and topography.
Output files for each of these will only be output if there is input data that 
correspond to these. If you only have input data for grid locations -- you will only
get an output grid file. If you have both grid and fraction data you will get grid and
fraction data files. If you also have topography data you will also get topo files.
</para>
<para>
Namelist options to <command>mkgriddata</command> include:
<simplelist>
<member><varname>mksrf_fnavyoro</varname> -- Navy orography file to use for land fraction
and surface heights.</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_frawtopo</varname> -- Raw topography file with just surface
heights.</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fcamfile</varname> -- <acronym>CAM</acronym> initial conditions file with
land-fractions and topography</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fclmgrid</varname> -- &clm; grid file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fccsmdom</varname> -- &cesm; domain file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fcamtopo</varname> -- <acronym>CAM</acronym> topography file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_lsmlon</varname> -- number of longitude for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_lsmlat</varname>number of latitudes for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgen</varname> -- Northern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgee</varname> -- Southern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edges</varname> -- Eastern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgew</varname> -- Western edge for regional grid</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
<para>
You need to enter one of the following four options:
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fnavyoro    - high resolution topo dataset (topo data)
   mksrf_lsmlon      - number of longitudes
   mksrf_lsmlat      - number of latitudes
   mksrf_edgen       - northern edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edgee       - eastern  edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edges       - southern edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edgew       - western  edge of grid (degrees)
</screen>
or
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fcamfile    - <acronym>CAM</acronym> topo file (grid and possibly fraction data)
</screen>
or 
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fccsmdom    - &cesm; domain file (both grid, and fraction data)
</screen>
or
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fclmgrid    - &clm; grid or surface dataset file (grid data)
</screen>
Note, you can provide more than one of the needed datasets, and the output
data will be determined by the datasets according to an order of precedence.
The order of precedence for data is as follows:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fcamfile</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fclmgrid</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fnavyoro</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fccsmdom</filename></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
Grid data then will be established by the file with the highest precedence. 
&cesm; domain files sometimes have latitudes and longitudes that are "off" from
the standard by a small amount. By establishing an order of precedence you can ensure
that grid locations exactly match a given standard file, even if the values in the domain
file are off from that.
</para>

<para>
There are three different major modes for using "mkgriddata" to create grid files
for &clm;:
<simplelist>
<member><varname>mksrf_fnavyoro</varname> -- Navy orography file to use for land fraction
and surface heights.</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_frawtopo</varname> -- Raw topography file with just surface
heights.</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fcamfile</varname> -- <acronym>CAM</acronym> initial conditions file with
land-fractions and topography</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fclmgrid</varname> -- &clm; grid file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fccsmdom</varname> -- &cesm; domain file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_fcamtopo</varname> -- <acronym>CAM</acronym> topography file</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_lsmlon</varname> -- number of longitude for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_lsmlat</varname> -- number of latitudes for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgen</varname> -- Northern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgee</varname> -- Southern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edges</varname> -- Eastern edge for regional grid</member>
<member><varname>mksrf_edgew</varname> -- Western edge for regional grid</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
<para>
You need to enter one of the following four options:
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fnavyoro    - high resolution topo dataset (topo data)
   mksrf_lsmlon      - number of longitudes
   mksrf_lsmlat      - number of latitudes
   mksrf_edgen       - northern edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edgee       - eastern  edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edges       - southern edge of grid (degrees)
   mksrf_edgew       - western  edge of grid (degrees)
</screen>
or
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fcamfile    - <acronym>CAM</acronym> topo file (grid and possibly fraction data)
</screen>
or 
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fccsmdom    - &cesm; domain file (both grid, and fraction data)
</screen>
or
<screen width="99">
   mksrf_fclmgrid    - &clm; grid or surface dataset file (grid data)
</screen>
Note, you can provide more than one of the needed datasets, and the output
data will be determined by the datasets according to an order of precedence.
The order of precedence for data is as follows:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fcamfile</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fclmgrid</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fnavyoro</filename></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><filename>mksrf_fccsmdom</filename></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
Grid data then will be established by the file with the highest precedence. 
&cesm; domain files sometimes have latitudes and longitudes that are "off" from
the standard by a small amount. By establishing an order of precedence you can ensure
that grid locations exactly match a given standard file, even if the values in the domain
file are off from that.
</para>

<para>
There are three different major modes for using <command>mkgriddata</command> to 
create grid files for &clm;:
<simplelist>
<member>Convert &cesm; domain files to &clm; grid files</member>
<member>Create single point or regional area grid files</member>
<member>Convert <acronym>CAM</acronym> files to &clm; grid files</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mkgriddata_from_domainfile">
<title>Convert &cesm; domain files to &clm; grid files</title>
<para>
&cesm; domain files such as used for &datm;, include all the information
needed to create &clm; grid and fraction files.
<example>
<title>Example <command>mkgriddata</command> namelist to convert &cesm; 4x5 domain files to &clm; grid files</title>
<screen width="99">
&amp;clmexp
 mksrf_fccsmdom=
'/fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/lnd/dlnd7/domain.lnd.4x5_gx3v5.060404.nc'
 mksrf_fclmgrid=
'/fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/lnd/clm2/griddata/griddata_4x5_060404.nc'
/
</screen>
</example>
<tip>
<para>
Notice that in the above example, a &clm; grid file is included as well, even though
it's not required. The reason for this is to ensure that the latitude and longitudes
on the output files exactly match a standard grid file.
</para>
</tip>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mkgriddata_regional">
<title>Create single point or regional area grid files</title>
<para>
The process to create single-point or regional area &clm; grid files is the same.
You enter the number of latitudes and longitudes you want on your output file and
the extent of the grid: North, East, South and West. You also tell 
<command>mkgriddata</command> that
you are entering a "regional" grid and you also enter the standard Navy orography
dataset (or your own orography file if desired). For a single point you simply
enter "1" for the number of latitudes and longitudes, but you still enter the
grid extent (of the single grid cell). Here is a sample regional namelist to create
a 5x5 regional grid over the Amazon:
<example>
<title>Example <command>mkgriddata</command> namelist to create regional grid over Amazon</title>
<screen width="99">
&amp;clmexp
 mksrf_fnavyoro=
"/fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/lnd/clm2/rawdata/mksrf_navyoro_20min.c010129.nc"
 mksrf_lsmlon = 5
 mksrf_lsmlat = 5
 mksrf_edgee = 303.75
 mksrf_edgew = 286.25
 mksrf_edges = -15.
 mksrf_edgen = -4.
/
</screen>
</example>
</para>
<warning>
<para>
Currently you can <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> have regional grids that straddle both
sides of the Greenwich (longitude = zero) line.
</para>
</warning>
<important>
<para>
You should enter longitudes with values from 0 to 360 East.
</para>
</important>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mkgriddata_from_camfile">
<title>Convert <acronym>CAM</acronym> files to &clm; grid files (deprecated)</title>
<para>
Older <acronym>CAM</acronym> initial files included all the information needed to create &clm;
grid files. Newer <acronym>CAM</acronym> files no longer include land fraction data. Hence you
can use <acronym>CAM</acronym> files to give you the grid coordinates, but you need other data
to give you the land-mask and topography. Since, <acronym>CAM</acronym> files no longer
contain the needed information, this option is now deprecated. In most cases you should
use one of the other two options.
</para>
</sect2>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="mkdatadomain">
<title>Using <command>mkdatadomain</command> to create domain datasets for &datm; or docn from &clm; grid datasets</title>
<para>
"mkdatadomain" is used to convert &clm; grid and fraction datasets into domain datasets
that can be used by either the "datm" or "docn" models. Most often &clm; users will want
to convert the grid datasets they just created using <command>mkgriddata</command> into
domain datasets to be used by &datm; for an "I" case. <command>mkdatadomain</command> is
controlled by a namelist, and has a very straight forward operation with only four
namelist items all of which are required. You specify which output mode you want "datm"
or "docn", and then set the input &clm; grid and frac datasets, and the output domain file.
</para>
<example>
<title>Example <command>mkdatadomain</command> namelist to create a domain file from 
&clm; frac and grid data files</title>
<screen width="99">
&amp;domain_nl
 dtype = "datm"
 f_fracdata = 
'/fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/lnd/clm2/griddata/fracdata_4x5_USGS_070110.nc'
 f_griddata = 
'/fs/cgd/csm/inputdata/lnd/clm2/griddata/griddata_4x5_060404.nc'
 f_domain   = 
'domain.lnd.fv4x5_USGS.090117.nc'
/
</screen>
</example>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="mksurfdata">
<title>Using mksurfdata to create surface datasets from grid datasets</title>
<para>
<command>mksurfdata</command> is used to create surface-datasets from grid datasets and raw datafiles
at half-degree resolution to produce files that describe the surface characteristics
needed by &clm; (fraction of grid cell covered by different land-unit types, and fraction
for different vegetation types, as well as things like soil color, and soil texture,
etc.). To run <command>mksurfdata</command> you can either use the
<command>mksurfdata.pl</command> script which will create namelists for you using the &buildnml;
XML database, or you can run it by hand using a namelist that you provide (possibly
modeled after an example provided in the
<filename>models/lnd/clm/tools/mksurfdata</filename> directory). The namelist for 
<command>mksurfdata</command> is sufficiently complex that we recommend using the 
<command>mksurfdata.pl</command> tool to build them. In the next section
we describe how to use the <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> script and the following
section gives more details on running <command>mksurfdata</command> by hand and the
various namelist input variables to it.
</para>
<sect2 id="mksurfdata.pl">
<title>Running <command>mksurfdata.pl</command></title>
<para>
The script <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> can be used to run the 
<command>mksurfdata</command> program for several configurations, resolutions, 
simulation-years and simulation year ranges. It will create the needed namelists for 
you and move the files
over to your inputdata directory location (and create a list of the files created, and
for developers this file is also a script to import the files into the svn inputdata
repository). It will also use the &buildnml; XML database
to determine the correct input files to use, and for transient cases it will create
the appropriate <filename>mksrf_fdynuse</filename> file with the list of files for each
year needed for this case. And in the case of urban single-point 
datasets (where surface datasets are actually input into <command>mksurfdata</command>)
it will do the additional processing required so that the output dataset
can be used once again by <command>mksurfdata</command>. Because, it figures out
namelist and input files for you, it is recommended that you use this script for creation
of standard surface datasets. If you need to create surface datasets for customized
cases, you might need to run <command>mksurfdata</command> on it's own. But you
could use <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> with the "-debug" option to give you
a namelist to start from.
For help on <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> you can use the "-help" option as below:
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/tools/mksurfdata
> mksurdata.pl -help
</screen>
The output of the above command is:
<screen width="99">
&mksurfdatapl;
</screen>
</para>
<para>
To run the script with optimized <command>mksurfdata</command> for a 4x5 degree grid 
for 1850 conditions, on bluefire you would do the following:
<example id="example_mksurfdata.pl">
<title>Example of running <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> to create a 4x5 resolution
<filename>fsurdat</filename> for a 1850 simulation year</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/tools/mksurfdata
> gmake
> mksurfdata.pl -y 1850 -r 4x5
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="mksurfdata_byhand">
<title>Running <command>mksurfdata</command> by Hand</title>
<para>
In the above section we show how to run <command>mksurfdata</command> through
the <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> using input datasets that are in the &buildnml;
XML database. When you are running with input datasets that are NOT available in
the XML database you either need to add them as outlined in 
<xref linkend="adding_files"></xref>, or you need to run <command>mksurfdata</command> 
by hand, as we will outline here.
</para>

<sect3 id="mksurfdata_namelist">
<title>Preparing your <command>mksurfdata</command> namelist</title>
<para>
When running <command>mksurfdata</command> by hand you will need to prepare your
own input namelist. There are sample namelists that are setup for running on the
&ncar; machine bluefire. You will need to change the filepaths to
run on a different machine. The list of sample namelists include
<simplelist>
<member><filename>mksurfdata.namelist</filename> -- standard sample namelist.</member>
<member><filename>mksurfdata.regional</filename> -- sample namelist to
build for a regional grid dataset (5x5_amazon)</member>
<member><filename>mksurfdata.singlept</filename> -- sample namelist to
build for a single point grid dataset (1x1_brazil)</member>
</simplelist>
Note, that one of the inputs <varname>mksrf_fdynuse</varname> is a filename that
includes the filepaths to other files. The filepaths in this file will have to
be changed as well. You also need to make sure that the line lengths remain the same
as the read is a formatted read, so the placement of the year in the file, must remain
the same, even with the new filenames. One advantage of the <command>mksurfdata.pl</command>
script is that it will create the <varname>mksrf_fdynuse</varname> file for you.
</para>
<para>
We list the namelist items below. Most of the namelist items are filepaths to give to
the input half degree resolution datasets that you will use to scale from to the
resolution of your grid dataset.
You must first specify the input grid dataset for the resolution to output for:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fgrid</varname> Grid dataset</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
Then you must specify settings for input high resolution datafiles
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_ffrac</varname> land fraction and land mask dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fglacier</varname> Glacier dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_flai</varname> Leaf Area Index dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_flanwat</varname> Land water dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_forganic</varname> Organic soil carbon dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fmax</varname> Max fractional saturated area dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fsoicol</varname> Soil color dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fsoitex</varname> Soil texture dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_ftopo</varname> Topography dataset (this is used to limit
the extent of urban regions and is used for glacier multiple elevation classes)
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_furban</varname> Urban dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fvegtyp</varname> PFT vegetation type dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fvocef</varname> Volatile Organic Compound Emission Factor
dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fgdp</varname> GDP dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fpeat</varname> Peatland dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fabm</varname> Agricultural fire peak month dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_ftopostats</varname> Topography statistics dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fvic</varname> VIC parameters dataset</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fch4</varname> Inversion-derived CH4 parameters dataset</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
You specify the ASCII text file with the land-use files.
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_fdynuse</varname> "dynamic land use" for transient
land-use/land-cover changes. This is an ASCII text file that lists the filepaths
to files for each year and then the year it represents (note: you MUST change the
filepaths inside the file when running on a machine NOT at &ncar;).
We always use this file, even for creating datasets of a fixed year. Also note
that when using the "pft_" settings this file will be an XML-like file with settings
for PFT's rather than filepaths (see <xref linkend="mksurfdata_exp"></xref> below).
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
And optionally you can specify settings for:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><varname>all_urban</varname> If entire area is urban (typically used for
single-point urban datasets, that you want to be exclusively urban)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>no_inlandwet</varname> If TRUE, set wetland to 0% over land
(renormalizing other landcover types as needed); wetland will only be used for ocean
points. (Only applies to CLM4.5 version of mksurfdata_map, for which the default is
TRUE.)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_firrig</varname> Irrigation dataset, if you want
activate the irrigation model over generic cropland
(experimental mode, normally NOT used)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_gridnm</varname> Name of output grid resolution (if not
set the files will be named according to the number of longitudes by latitudes)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>mksrf_gridtype</varname> Type of grid (default is 'global')</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>nglcec</varname> number of glacier multiple elevation classes.
Can be 0, 1, 3, 5, or 10. When using the resulting dataset with &clm; you can then run
with <varname>glc_nec</varname> of either 0 or this value.
 (experimental normally use the default of 0, when running with the land-ice
model in practice only 10 has been used)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>numpft</varname> number of Plant Function Types (PFT) 
in the input vegetation <varname>mksrf_fvegtyp</varname> dataset. You change
this to 20, if you want to create a dataset with prognostic crop activated. The
vegetation dataset also needs to have prognostic crop types on it as well.
 (experimental normally not changed from the default of 16)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>outnc_large_files</varname> If output should be in &netcdf; large file
format</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>outnc_double</varname> If output should be in double
precision (normally we turn this on)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>pft_frc</varname> array of fractions to override PFT
data with for all gridpoints (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>pft_idx</varname> array of PFT indices to override PFT
data with for all gridpoints (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>soil_clay</varname> percent clay soil to override
all gridpoints with (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>soil_color</varname> Soil color to override
all gridpoints with (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>soil_fmax</varname> Soil maximum fraction to override
all gridpoints with (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><varname>soil_sand</varname> percent sandy soil to
override all gridpoints with (experimental mode, normally NOT used).</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
<para>
After creating your namelist,
when running on a non &ncar; machine you will need to get the files
from the inputdata repository.
In order to retrieve the files needed for mksurfdata you can do the following on your
namelist to get the files from the inputdata repository, using the
<command>check_input_data</command> script which also allows you to export data to
your local disk.
<example id="getmksurfdata_datasets">
<title>Getting the raw datasets for <command>mksurfdata</command> to your local 
machine using the <command>check_input_data</command> script</title>
<screen width="99">
> cd models/lnd/clm/tools/mksurfdata
# First remove any quotes and copy into a filename that can be read by the
# check_input_data script
> sed "s/'//g" namelist > clm.input_data_list
# Run the script with -export and give the location of your inputdata with $CSMDATA
> ../../../../../scripts/ccsm_utils/Tools/check_input_data -datalistdir . \
-inputdata $CSMDATA -check -export
# You must then do the same with the fdynuse file referred to in the namelist
# in this case we add a file = to the beginning of each line
> awk '{print "file = "$1}' pftdyn_hist_simyr2000-2000.txt > clm.input_data_list
# Run the script with -export and give the location of your inputdata with $CSMDATA
> ../../../../../scripts/ccsm_utils/Tools/check_input_data -datalistdir . \
-inputdata $CSMDATA -check -export
</screen>
</example>
</para>
<sect4 id="mksurfdata_exp">
<title>Experimental options to <command>mksurfdata</command></title>
<para>
The options: pft_frc, pft_idx, soil_clay, soil_color, soil_fmax, and soil_sand are also
new and considered experimental. They provide a way to override the PFT and soil
values for all grid points to the given values that you set. This is useful for
running with single-point tower sites where the soil type and vegetation is known.
Note that when you use pft_frc, all other landunits will be zeroed out, and the
sum of your pft_frc array MUST equal 100.0. Also note that when using the "pft_" 
options the <filename>mksrf_fdynuse</filename> file instead of having filepath's
will be an XML-like file with PFT settings. Unlike the file of file-paths, you will
have to create this file by hand, <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> will NOT be able
to create it for you (other than the first year which will be set to the values 
entered on the command line). Note, that when &ptclm; is run, it CAN create these
files for you from a simpler format (see <xref linkend="PTCLMDynPFTFiles"></xref>).
Instead of a filepath you have a list of XML elements that give information on the PFT's
and harvesting for example:
<screen width="99">
&lt;pft_f&gt;100&lt;/pft_f&gt;&lt;pft_i&gt;1&lt;/pft_i&gt;&lt;harv&gt;0,0,0,0,0&lt;/harv&gt;&lt;graz&gt;0&lt;/graz&gt;
</screen>
So the &lt;pft_f&gt; tags give the PFT fractions and the &lt;pft_i&gt; tags give the
index for that fraction. Harvest is an array of five elements, and grazing is a single
value. Like the usual file each list of XML elements goes with a year, and there is 
limit on the number of characters that can be used.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="mksurfdata_sop">
<title>Standard Practices when using <command>mksurfdata</command></title>
<para>
In this section we give the recommendations for how to use <command>mksurfdata</command>
to give similar results to the files that we created when using it.
</para>
<para>
If you look at the standard surface datasets that we have created and provided for use,
there are three practices that we have consistently done in each (you also see these in
the sample namelists and in the <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> script). The first is 
that we always output data in double precision (hence <varname>outnc_double</varname> 
is set to <literal>.true.</literal>). The next is that we always use the procedure 
for creating transient datasets (using <varname>mksrf_fdynuse</varname>) even when 
creating datasets for a fixed simulation year. This is to ensure that the fixed year
datasets will be consistent with the transient datasets. When this is done a 
"surfdata.pftdyn" dataset will be created -- but will NOT be used in &clm;. If you look
at the sample namelist <filename>mksurfdata.namelist</filename> you note that it
sets <varname>mksrf_fdynuse</varname> to the file
<filename>pftdyn_hist_simyr2000.txt</filename>, where the single file entered is
the same PFT file used in the rest of the namelist (as <varname>mksrf_fvegtyp</varname>).
The last practice that we always do is to always set <varname>mksrf_ftopo</varname>,
even if glacier elevation classes are NOT active. This is
important in limiting urban areas based on topographic height, and hence is important
to use all the time. The glacier multiple elevation classes will be used as well if
you are running a compset with the active glacier model.
</para>
<para>
There are two other important practices for creating urban single point datasets. The
first is that you often will want to set <varname>all_urban</varname> to
<literal>.true.</literal> so that the dataset will have 100% of the gridcell output
as urban rather than some mix of: urban, vegetation types, and other landunits. The
next practice is that most of our specialized urban datasets have custom values for
the urban parameters, hence we do NOT want to use the global urban dataset to get
urban parameters -- we use a previous version of the surface dataset for the urban
parameters. However, in order to do this, we need to append onto the previous surface
dataset the grid and land mask/land fraction information from the grid and fraction
datasets. This is done in <command>mksurfdata.pl</command> using the <acronym>NCO</acronym>
program <command>ncks</command>. An example of doing this for the Mexico City, Mexico
urban surface dataset is as follows:
<screen width="99">
> ncks -A $CSMDATA/lnd/clm2/griddata/griddata_1x1pt_mexicocityMEX_c090715.nc \
$CSMDATA/lnd/clm2/surfdata/surfdata_1x1_mexicocityMEX_simyr2000_c100407.nc
> ncks -A $CSMDATA/lnd/clm2/griddata/fracdata_1x1pt_mexicocityMEX_navy_c090715.nc \
$CSMDATA/lnd/clm2/surfdata/surfdata_1x1_mexicocityMEX_simyr2000_c100407.nc
</screen>
Note, if you look at the current single point urban surface datasets you will note
that the above has already been done.
</para>
<para>
The final issue is how to build <command>mksurfdata</command>. When NOT optimized
<command>mksurfdata</command> is very slow, and can take many hours to days to
even run for medium resolutions such as one or two degree. So usually you will want
to run it optimized. Possibly you also want to use shared memory parallelism using 
&omp; with the <envar>SMP</envar> option. The problem with running optimized is that
answers will be different when running optimized versus non-optimized for most
compilers. So if you want answers to be the same as a previous surface dataset, you
will need to run it on the same platform and optimization level. Likewise, running
with or without &omp; may also change answers (for most compilers it will NOT, however
it does for the IBM compiler). However, answers should be the same regardless of the
number of threads used when &omp; is enabled. Note, that the output surface datasets
will have attributes that describe whether the file was written out optimized or not,
with threading or not and the number of threads used, to enable the user to more
easily try to match datasets created previously. For more information on the different
compiler options for the &clm4; tools see <xref linkend="tool_build"></xref>.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="ncl_scripts">
<title>Using &ncl; scripts <command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> and 
<command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command> to interpolate aerosol deposition datasets</title>
<para>
Unlike the other tools, these are &ncar; Command Language (&ncl;) scripts
and you will need to get a copy of &ncl; in order to use them. You also won't have to
build an executable in order to use them, hence no Makefile is provided. &ncl; is provided
for free download as either binaries or source code from:
<ulink url="http://www.ncl.ucar.edu/">http://www.ncl.ucar.edu/</ulink>. The &ncl;
web-site also contains documentation on &ncl; and it's use.
</para>
<para>
By default at this point neither of these scripts <emphasis>HAS</emphasis> to be used,
as the model is now constructed to read aerosol and Nitrogen deposition from 2-degree
datasets and interpolate to the model resolution on the fly. The main reason you might
want to do this now, is for better performance for single-point simulations.
</para>
<para>
Both the <command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> and <command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command>
scripts have similar interfaces and you customize the output resolution and
characteristics based on the settings of environment variables that you set (if you
don't set any of the variables, the script has defaults that it will use).
The list of environment variables that can be set are:
<simplelist>
<member><envar>RES</envar> -- output resolution name</member>
<member><envar>RCP</envar> -- representative concentration pathway for future scenarios
(example 2.6, 4.5, 6, or 8.5)</member>
<member><envar>SIM_YR</envar> -- simulation year (example 1850 or 2000)</member>
<member><envar>SIM_YR_RNG</envar> -- simulation year range (example 1850-2000 or
1850-2100)</member>
<member><envar>GRDFIL</envar> -- full pathname of grid file to use 
(in place of getting the default grid file based on the <envar>RES</envar> value)</member>
<member><envar>CSMDATA</envar> -- &cesm; inputdata directory</member>
<member><envar>CLM_ROOT</envar> -- root directory for &clm; (models/lnd/clm directory)</member>
</simplelist>
</para>
<important>
<para>
You <emphasis>MUST</emphasis> provide either <envar>RES</envar> or both
<envar>GRDFIL</envar> <emphasis>AND</emphasis> <envar>RES</envar>. If you
just give <envar>RES</envar> the default namelist database in
<filename>models/lnd/clm/bld</filename> will be used to find the default grid
file based on the resolution name <envar>RES</envar>. If you provide
<envar>GRDFIL</envar> the input pathname of the gridfile provided will be used,
and the output filename will include <envar>RES</envar> as part of it's name
to designate it as an output file at that resolution.
</para>
</important>
<para>
Both scripts assume that you will be interpolating from a native resolution of 1.9x2.5
and using the default files found in the namelist database to interpolate from. If you
want to interpolate from another resolution or use other files, you would need to edit
the scripts to do so. Both scripts also use a bilinear interpolation to do the
regridding. The environment variables: <envar>RCP</envar>, <envar>SIM_YR</envar>,
and <envar>SIM_YR_RNG</envar> will be used to query the namelist database to 
determine which native dataset to interpolate from. If you don't provide valid
values for these variables, it won't be able to find a dataset to interpolate from.
You can use the build-namelist script to query what the valid values for these can
be. Likewise, when you use <envar>RES</envar> to determine the grid file to interpolate
to, it needs to be a valid value from the namelist database.
</para>
<para>
The scripts can be used to interpolate from (and create output) constant or
transient datasets.
Constant datasets specify the <envar>SIM_YR</envar> and set <envar>SIM_YR_RNG</envar>
to <varname>constant</varname> (which is also the default). Transient datasets need
to specify both <envar>SIM_YR</envar> and <envar>SIM_YR_RNG</envar>, where 
<envar>SIM_YR</envar> is set to the first year in the interval (typically 1850).
</para>
<para>
The default for <envar>CSMDATA</envar> works for &ncar; computers, but will need to
be set to the top level directory location of your &cesm; input data on other computers.
If you set this as a default for your shell when you login (for example with your
<filename>$HOME/.cshrc</filename> if you use csh) you won't have to set it each time
you run the script. <envar>CLM_ROOT</envar> will default to the proper location
when you run it in the <filename>models/lnd/clm/tools/ncl_script</filename>
directory. It is only useful if you want to run the script out of a different 
directory.
</para>
<sect2 id="ndepregrid">
<title>Using <command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> to interpolate Nitrogen deposition datasets</title>
<para>
<command>ndepregrid.ncl</command> interpolates the Nitrogen deposition datasets from one resolution
to another.
</para>
<note>
<para>
Interpolating Nitrogen deposition files is no longer needed, because the model can
read Nitrogen deposition files at one resolution and interpolate to the resolution the
model is running at on the fly. Interpolating to another
resolution is only useful for very course resolutions, if you want to save some computing
resources in reading larger datasets. For example, this may be useful in obtaining 
single-point datasets.
</para>
</note>
<para>
For example, to interpolate to an output resolution of 0.9x1.25, for a constant
simulation-year of 1850, you would do the following:
<screen width="99">
> env RES=0.9x1.25 SIM_YR=1850 ncl ndepregrid.ncl
</screen>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="aerdepregrid">
<title>Using <command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command> to interpolate Aerosol deposition datasets</title>
<para>
<command>aerdepregrid.ncl</command> interpolates the Aerosol deposition datasets from one resolution.
It can be used to interpolate either constant datasets (for example:
<filename>aerosoldep_monthly_2000_0.9x1.25_c090828.nc</filename>) or transient datasets (for example:
<filename>aerosoldep_monthly_1849-2006_0.9x1.25_c090830.nc</filename>).
</para>
<note>
<para>
Interpolating aerosol deposition files is no longer needed, because the &datm; model can
read aerosol deposition files at one resolution and interpolate to the resolution the
model is running at on the fly.  Interpolating to another
resolution is only useful for very course resolutions, if you want to save some computing
resources in reading larger datasets. For example, this may be useful in obtaining 
single-point datasets.
</para>
</note>
<para>
For example, to interpolate to an output resolution of 4x5, for a transient
simulation-year range of 1850 to 2100 and the rcp of 8.5, you would do the following:
<screen width="99">
> env RES=4x5 SIM_YR=1850 SIM_YR_RNG=1850-2100 RCP=8.5 ncl ndepregrid.ncl
</screen>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="customizing_files">
<title>How to Customize Datasets for particular Observational Sites</title>
<para>
There are two ways to customize datasets for a particular observational site. The first
is to customize the input to the tools that create the dataset, and the second is to
over-write the default data after you've created a given dataset. Depending on the tool
it might be easier to do it one way or the other. In <xref
linkend="table_required_files"></xref> we list the files that are most likely to be
customized and the way they might be customized. Of those files, the ones you are most
likely to customize are: fatmlndfrc, fsurdat, faerdep (for &datm;), and 
stream_fldfilename_ndep.  Note <command>mksurfdata</command> as documented previously
has options to overwrite the vegetation and soil types. For more information on this also see
<xref linkend="own_single_point_datasets"></xref> and &ptclm; uses these methods to
customize datasets see <xref linkend="PTCLMDOC"></xref>.
</para>
<para>
Another aspect of customizing your input datasets is customizing the input atmospheric
forcing datasets. See the <xref linkend="own_atm_forcing"></xref> for more
information on this. Also the chapter on &ptclm; in <xref linkend="AmeriFluxdata"></xref> 
has information on using the AmeriFlux tower site data as atmospheric forcing.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="tools_conclude">
<title>Conclusion of tools description</title>
<para>
We've given a description of how to use the different tools with &clm; to create
customized datasets. In the next chapter we will talk about how to make these
files available for build-namelist so that you can easily create simulations
that include them. In the chapter on single-point and regional datasets we also
give an alternative way to enter new datasets without having to edit files.
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>
<!-- End of tools chapter -->
