<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entries>

  <entry id="COMP_GLC"> 
    <type>char</type>
    <valid_values>cism</valid_values>
    <default_value>cism</default_value>
    <group>case_comp</group>
    <file>env_case.xml</file>
    <desc>Name of land ice-sheet component</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CISM_USE_TRILINOS">
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <default_value>FALSE</default_value>
    <group>build_component_cism</group>
    <file>env_build.xml</file>
    <desc>TRUE implies CISM is built with support for the trilinos library
      When using the higher-order dynamical cores in CISM, one option is to
      use the trilinos solver library for sparse matrix solves. In order to
      exercise that option, you need to build CISM with trilinos support, and
      link to the trilinos libraries when building the CESM executable. Setting
      this variable to TRUE accomplishes these things. Note that you can set
      this to TRUE and still choose not to use the trilinos solvers for the
      sparse matrix solves. Also, note that trilinos is only available on a
      limited set of machines; this must remain FALSE to run CISM on a
      machine that does not have trilinos, or for which the CESM scripts are
      not aware of the existence of trilinos.</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CISM_PHYS">
    <type>char</type>
    <valid_values>cism1,cism2</valid_values>
    <default_value>cism1</default_value>
    <values>
      <value compset="CISM1">cism1</value>
      <value compset="CISM2">cism2</value>
    </values>
    <group>run_component_cism</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>Version of CISM physics/dynamics to use</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="CISM_OBSERVED_IC">
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
    <default_value>FALSE</default_value>
    <group>run_component_cism</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>For hybrid runs, whether CISM should use observed initial conditions 
      instead of restart file.
      For hybrid runs, a value of FALSE (default) implies that CISM should
      use the restart file from the reference case; a value of TRUE implies
      that CISM should instead use the observed initial conditions that are
      generally used for startup runs. This variable is ignored for startup
      runs; for branch runs, it MUST BE FALSE.</desc>
  </entry>

  <entry id="GLC_SMB"> 
    <type>logical</type>
    <valid_values>true,false</valid_values>
    <default_value>true</default_value>
    <group>run_component_cism</group>
    <file>env_run.xml</file>
    <desc>true => do surface mass balance, false => PDD, nec_glc is set to 1</desc>
  </entry>

  <description>
    <desc compset="_CISM1">cism1:</desc>
    <desc compset="_CISM2">cism2:</desc>
  </description>

  <help>
    =========================================
    CISM naming conventions in compset name
    =========================================
    CISM1  => cism1 (default, serial only)
    CISM2  => cism2 (higher-order, can run in parallel)
  </help>

</entries>
