<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="namelist_definition.xsl"?>

<namelist_definition>

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- DATM env settings                         -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="DATM_MODE" 
type="char*256"  
category="datm_setting"
group="datm_env_settings" 
valid_values="CLM_QIAN">
Data Model mode to process forcing data
</entry>

<entry id="DATM_PRESAERO" 
type="char*256"  
category="datm_setting"
group="datm_env_settings" 
valid_values="clim_2000">
Prescribed aerosol mode
</entry>

<!-- ========================================================================================  -->
<!-- DATM Namelists                                                                            -->
<!-- ========================================================================================  -->

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- shr_strmdata_nml (file datm_atm_in)       -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="datamode" 
type="char*256"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="CLMNCEP">
</entry>

<entry id="domainfile" 
type="char*256" 
category="streams"
input_pathname="abs" 
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
spatial gridfile associated with the strdata.  grid information will
be read from this file and that grid will serve as the target grid
for all input data for this strdata input.  
</entry>

<entry id="fillalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"
valid_values="copy,bilinear,nn,nnoni,nnonj,spval">
array (up to 30 elements) of fill algorithms associated with the array
of streams.  valid options are just copy (ie. no fill), special value,
nearest neighbor, nearest neighbor in "i" direction, or nearest
neighbor in "j" direction.
valid values:  'copy','spval','nn','nnoni','nnonj'  
default: "nn".
</entry>

<entry id="fillmask"
type="char*256(30)"
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask">
plays no role is fill algorithm at the present time.  
valid values: "nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask"
default: "nomask"
</entry>

<entry id="fillread" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to read in instead of computing the
weights on the fly for the fill operation.  if this is set, fillalgo
and fillmask are ignored.
default: unset
</entry>

<entry id="fillwrite" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml">
array (up to 30 elements)  of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to generate after weights are
computed on the fly for the fill operation.  this allows a user to
save and reuse a set of weights later.  
default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="mapmask" 
type="char*256(30)"
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"
valid_values="nomask,srcmask,dstmask,bothmask">
array (up to 30 elements) of masking algorithms for mapping input data
associated with the array of streams.  valid options are map only from
valid src points, map only to valid destination points, ignore all
masks, map only from valid src points to valid destination points.
valid values: srcmask, dstmask, nomask,bothmask
default: dstmask
</entry>

<entry id="mapalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="copy,bilinear,nn,nnoni,nnonj,spval">
array (up to 30 elements) of fill algorithms associated with the array
of streams.  valid options are copy by index, set to special value,
nearest neighbor, nearest neighbor in "i" direction, nearest neighbor
in "j" direction, or bilinear.  
valid values: copy,spval,nn,nnoni,nnonj,bilinear
default: bilinear
</entry>

<entry id="mapread" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml"> 
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to read instead of computing
weights on the fly for the mapping (interpolation) operation.  if this
is set, mapalgo and mapmask are ignored.  default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="mapwrite" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of filenames associated with the array of
streams.  specifies the weights file to generate after weights are
computed on the fly for the mapping (interpolation) operation.  this
allows a user to save and reuse a set of weights later.
default="unset".
</entry>

<entry id="tintalgo" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="coszen,nearest,linear,lower,upper">
array (up to 30 elements) of time interpolation options associated with the array of
streams.  
valid values: lower,upper,nearest,linear,coszen
  lower   = Use lower time-value
  upper   = Use upper time-value
  nearest = Use the nearest time-value
  linear  = Linearly interpolate between the two time-values
  coszen  = Scale according to the cosine of the solar zenith angle (for solar)
default="linear".
</entry>

<entry id="taxmode" 
type="char*256(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" 
valid_values="extend,cycle,limit">
array of time axis modes associated with the array of streams for
handling data outside the specified stream time axis.  
valid options are to cycle the data based on the first, last, and
align settings associated with the stream dataset, to extend the first
and last valid value indefinitely, or to limit the interpolated data
to fall only between the least and greatest valid value of the time array.
valid values: cycle,extend,limit
default="cycle".
</entry>

<entry id="dtlimit" 
type="real(30)"  
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
array (up to 30 elements) of delta time ratio limits placed on the
time interpolation associated with the array of streams.  this real
value causes the model to stop if the ratio of the running maximum
delta time divided by the minimum delta time is greater than the
dtlimit for that stream.  for instance, with daily data, the delta
time should be exactly one day throughout the dataset and the computed
maximum divided by minimum delta time should always be 1.0.  for
monthly data, the delta time should be between 28 and 31 days and the
maximum ratio should be about 1.1.  the running value of the delta
time is computed as data is read and any wraparound or cycling is also
included.  this input helps trap missing data or errors in cycling.
to turn off trapping, set the value to 1.0e30 or something similar.
default=1.5. 
</entry>

<entry id="streams" 
type="char*256(30)" 
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
character array (up to 30 elements) of stream input files.  this
string is actually parsed by a stream method and so the format is
specified by the stream module.  this string consists of a
"stream_input_filename year_align year_first year_last".  the
stream_input_filename is a stream text input file and the format and
options are described elsewhere.  year_align, year_first, and
year_last provide information about the time axis of the file and how
to relate the input time axis to the model time axis.  
default="null".
</entry>

<entry id="vectors" 
type="char*256" 
category="streams"
group="shr_strdata_nml" >
list of paired colon delimited field names that should be treated as
vectors when carrying out spatial interpolation.  unlike other
character arrays in this namelist, this array is completely decoupled
from the list of streams.  this is a list of vector pairs that span
all input streams where different fields of the vector pair could
appear in different streams.  
for example, vectors = 'u:v','taux:tauy'.  
default="".
</entry>

<entry id="atm_in" 
type="char*256" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml">
The data atmosphere specific namelist input is as follows.  The
namelist input filename is hardwired in the data model code to
"datm_in".  The namelist group is called "datm_nml".  The variable
formats are character string (char), integer (int), double precision
real (r8), or logical (log) or one dimensional arrays of any of those
things.  atm_in sets the filename for the data atmosphere shr_strmdata namelist.
default: datm_atm_in.
</entry>

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- datm_nml (in file datm_in)                -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="decomp" 
type="char*4" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml" 
valid_values="1d,root" >
Set the decomposition option for the data model.  valid options are
placing the global array on the root task or a simple stride-one
load balanced one-dimensional decomposition.  other decompositions
may be added in the future.  
valid values are ['root','1d'].
  1d   = Vector decomposition
  root = run only on the master task
default='1d'. 
</entry>

<entry id="factorfn" 
type="char*256" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml" 
input_pathname="abs" >
filename containing correction factors for use only with CORE2 modes (CORE2_IAF and CORE2_NYF).
default='null'.  
</entry>

<entry id="presaero" 
type="logical" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml">
If TRUE, prescribed aerosols are sent from datm (must be true for running with CLM).
</entry>

<entry id="force_prognostic_true"
type="logical" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml">
If TRUE, prognostic is forced to true.
default=false 
</entry>

<entry id="iradsw" 
type="integer" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml" 
valid_values="">
Frequency to update radiation in number of steps (or hours if negative)
irdasw is the radiation setting used to compute the next shortwave
Julian date.  values greater than 1 set the next radiation to the
present time plus 2 timesteps every iradsw.  values less than 0 turn
set the next radiation to the present time plus two timesteps every
-iradsw hours.  if iradsw is zero, the next radiation time is the
present time plus 1 timestep.
default=0.
</entry>

<entry id="restfilm" 
type="char*256" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml" 
valid_values="">
Model restart filename for the data atmosphere model data.  This is
optional.  If both restfils and restfilm are undefined, the restart
filename will be read from the DATM restart pointer file (or files for multiple instances).
default='undefined'.
</entry>

<entry id="restfils" 
type="char*256" 
category="datm"
group="datm_nml" 
valid_values="">
Stream restart filename for the data atmosphere stream data.  This is
optional.  If both restfils and restfilm are undefined, the restart
filename will be read from the DATM restart pointer file (or files for multiple instances).
default='undefined'.
</entry>

<!-- =========================================  -->
<!--- modelio (in file atm_modeio.nml)          -->
<!-- =========================================  -->

<entry id="logfile" 
type="char*256" 
category="datm"
group="modelio" 
valid_values="">
DATM logfile name
default='atm.log'
</entry>

</namelist_definition>
