<?xml version="1.0"?>
<file id="env_build.xml" version="2.0">
  <header>
    These variables SHOULD NOT be changed once the model has been built.
    urrently, these variables are not cached.
    Note1: users SHOULD NOT modify BUILD_COMPETE below
    this is done automatically by the scripts.
    </header>
  <group id="build_grid">
    <entry id="GRID" value="a%CLM_USRDAT_l%CLM_USRDAT_oi%CLM_USRDAT_r%null_m%reg_g%null_w%null">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>Model grid - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ATM_GRID" value="CLM_USRDAT">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>atmosphere grid - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ATM_NX" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of atmosphere cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ATM_NY" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of atmosphere cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="LND_GRID" value="CLM_USRDAT">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>land grid - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="LND_NX" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of land cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="LND_NY" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of land cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="OCN_GRID" value="CLM_USRDAT">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>ocn grid - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="OCN_NX" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of ocn cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="OCN_NY" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of ocn cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ICE_GRID" value="CLM_USRDAT">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>ice grid (must equal ocn grid) - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ICE_NX" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of ice cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ICE_NY" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of ice cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ICE_NCAT" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of ice thickness categories - DO NOT EDIT (set by CICE configure)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ROF_GRID" value="null">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>river runoff (rof) grid</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ROF_NX" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of rof cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="ROF_NY" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of rof cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="GLC_GRID" value="null">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values>gland20,gland10,gland5,gland5UM,gland4,mpas.gis20km,mpas.ais20km,null</valid_values>
      <desc>glacier (glc) grid - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="GLC_NX" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of glc cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="GLC_NY" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of glc cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="WAV_GRID" value="null">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>wave model (wav) grid</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="WAV_NX" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of wav cells in i direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="WAV_NY" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <desc>number of wav cells in j direction - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="MASK_GRID" value="reg">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>grid mask - DO NOT EDIT (for experts only)</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_derived">
    <entry id="PERL5LIB">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>Perl 5 library directory</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="OBJROOT" value="$EXEROOT">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>case build directory (set automatically to $EXEROOT, - DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="LIBROOT" value="$EXEROOT/lib">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>case lib directory (set automatically to $EXEROOT/lib - DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="INCROOT" value="$EXEROOT/lib/include">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>case lib include directory (set automatically to $EXEROOT/lib/include - DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SHAREDLIBROOT" value="$EXEROOT">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Shared library root, (set automatically to $EXEROOT - DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_def">
    <entry id="CIME_OUTPUT_ROOT" value="/lustre/or-hydra/cades-ccsi/scratch/omearata">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Output root directory for each machine.
		Base directory for build and run directories.
    </desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="EXEROOT" value="$CIME_OUTPUT_ROOT/$CASE/bld">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Case executable root directory.
    (executable is $EXEROOT/$MODEL.exe, component libraries are in $EXEROOT/lib)
    This is where the model builds its executable and by default runs the executable.
    Note that EXEROOT needs to have enough disk space for the experimental configuration
    requirements. As an example, a model run can produce more than a terabyte of
    data during a 100-year run, so you should set EXEROOT to scratch or
    tmp space and frequently back up the data to a long term archiving storage device
    For a supported machine, EXEROOT is set in $CIMEROOT/machines/config_machines.xml.
    For a userdefined machine, EXEROOT must explicitly be set it in env_build.xml.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SUPPORTED_BY">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>email address of person (or group) that supports the build and port for this machine (do not edit)&gt;</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="CALENDAR" value="NO_LEAP">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values>NO_LEAP,GREGORIAN</valid_values>
      <desc>calendar type</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="COMP_INTERFACE" value="mct">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values>mct,nuopc</valid_values>
      <desc>use MCT component interface</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="USE_ESMF_LIB" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies using the ESMF library specified by ESMF_LIBDIR or ESMFMKFILE</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="DEBUG" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies turning on run and compile time debugging
      Flag to turn on debugging for run time and compile time.
      If TRUE, compile-time debugging flags are activated that you can use to verify
      software robustness, such as bounds checking.
      Important:: On IBM machines, floating point trapping is not activated for production
      runs (i.e., non-DEBUG), due to performance penalties associated with turning on these flags.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="BUILD_THREADED" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies always build model for openmp capability
      If FALSE, component libraries are built with OpenMP capability only if
      the NTHREADS_ setting for that component is greater than 1 in env_mach_pes.xml.
      If TRUE, the component libraries are always built with OpenMP capability.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SMP_PRESENT" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies that at least one of the components is built threaded (DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="USE_PETSC" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies linking to the PETSc library - set
    automatically by XXX_USE_PETSC options (do not edit). Flag to turn
    on linking to the PETSc library. Currently this is used by
    CLM. This is currently only supported for certain machines.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="USE_ALBANY" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies linking to the Albany library - set
    automatically by XXX_USE_ALBANY options (do not edit). Flag to
    turn on linking to the Albany library. Currently this is used by
    MPASLI. Note that Albany is a C++ library, so setting this
    variable to TRUE will involve the inclusion of C++ code in the
    MPASLI executable. This is currently only supported for certain
    machines.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="USE_MOAB" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies linking to the MOAB library</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="USE_TRILINOS" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies linking to the trilinos library - set automatically by XXX_USE_TRILINOS options (do not edit)
      Flag to turn on linking to the trilinos library. Currently this is
      used by CISM. Note that trilinos is a C++ library, so setting this
      variable to TRUE will involve the inclusion of C++ code in the model
      executable. This is currently only supported for certain machines.</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_macros">
    <entry id="OS" value="LINUX">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Operating system - DO NOT EDIT UNLESS for userdefined machine - ignored once Macros has been created.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="COMPILER" value="gnu">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Machine compiler (must match one the supported compilers)
    Set in $CIMEROOT/machines/config_machines.xml for each supported machine.
    Must be explicitly set in env_build.xml for userdefined machine.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="MPILIB" value="openmpi">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>mpi library (must match one of the supported libraries) -
    ignored once Macros has been created
    Set in $CIMEROOT/machines/config_machines.xml for each supported machine.
    Must be explicitly set in env_build.xml for userdefined machine.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="PIO_VERSION" value="1">
      <type>integer</type>
      <valid_values>1,2</valid_values>
      <desc>PIO library version</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="PIO_CONFIG_OPTS">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>PIO configure options, see PIO configure utility for details</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_status">
    <entry id="BUILD_COMPLETE" value="TRUE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>Status output: if TRUE, models have been built successfully. (DO NOT EDIT)&gt;</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SMP_BUILD" value="c0a0l0i0o0r0g0w0e0">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Status: smp status of previous build, coded string. (DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="SMP_VALUE" value="c0a0l0i0o0r0g0w0e0">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Status: smp status of current case, coded string (DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="NINST_BUILD" value="0">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Status: ninst status of previous build, coded string. (DO NOT EDIT)&gt;</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="NINST_VALUE" value="c1a1l1i1o1r1g1w1e1">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values/>
      <desc>Status: ninst status of current case, coded string (DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="BUILD_STATUS" value="0">
      <type>integer</type>
      <valid_values>0,1,2</valid_values>
      <desc>Status: of prior build. (DO NOT EDIT)</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_component_clm">
    <entry id="CLM_USE_PETSC" value="FALSE">
      <type>logical</type>
      <valid_values>TRUE,FALSE</valid_values>
      <desc>TRUE implies CLM is built with support for the PETSc
      library. The Variably Saturated Flow Model (VSFM) solver in CLM
      uses the PETSc library. In order to use the VSFM solver, CLM
      must be built with PETSc support and linking to PETSc must occur
      when building the ACME executable. This occurs if this variable
      is set to TRUE. Note that is only available on a limited set of
      machines/compilers.</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="CLM_CONFIG_OPTS" value="-phys clm4_5">
      <type>char</type>
      <desc>Provides option(s) for the CLM configure utility.
      CLM_CONFIG_OPTS are normally set as compset variables (e.g., -bgc cn)
      and in general should not be modified for supported compsets.
      It is recommended that if you want to modify this value for your experiment,
      you should use your own user-defined component sets via using create_newcase
      with a compset_file argument.
      This is an advanced flag and should only be used by expert users.</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
  <group id="build_component_rtm">
    <entry id="RTM_MODE" value="NULL">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values>ACTIVE,NULL</valid_values>
      <desc>mode for rtm model, NULL means rtm is turned off</desc>
    </entry>
    <entry id="RTM_FLOOD_MODE" value="NULL">
      <type>char</type>
      <valid_values>ACTIVE,NULL</valid_values>
      <desc>mode for rtm flood feature, NULL means rtm flood is turned off</desc>
    </entry>
  </group>
</file>
