<!-- Beg of special cases chapter -->
<chapter id="trouble">
<title>Trouble Shooting Problems</title>
<para>
In this chapter we give some guidance on what to do when you encounter some of the
most common problems. We can't cover all the problems that a user could potentially 
have, but we will try to help you recognize some of the most common situations.
And we'll give you some suggestions on how to approach the problem to come up with
a solution.
</para>
<para>
In general you will run into one of three type of problems:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>configure-time</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>build-time</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>run-time</emphasis></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
You may also run into problems with <command>create_newcase</command> itself, or
with the archiving scripts -- for those problems you should consult the 
<ulink url="&cesmwebmodelrel;cesm">&cesmrel; Scripts User's Guide</ulink>.
</para>

<sect1 id="trouble_w_configure">
<title>Trouble with Configuration</title>
<para>
The first type of problem happens when you invoke the <command>configure -case</command>
command. This indicates there is something wrong with your template files, or input
datasets, or the details of what you are trying to configure the model to do.
There's also a trouble-shooting chapter in the <ulink
url="&cesmwebmodelrel;cesm">&cesmrel;
Scripts User's Guide</ulink>. Many of the problems with configuration can be resolved
with the guidelines given there. Here we will restrict ourselves to problems from the
&clm; or &datm; templates or input files.
<example id="configure_problem">
<title>Example of configure problem with missing datasets</title>
<screen width="99">
> ./create_newcase -case T31rcp6 -res T31_g37 -compset IRCP60CN \
-mach bluefire
> ./configure -case
</screen>
<para>The following is what is displayed to the screen.</para>
<screen width="99">
Generating resolved namelist, prestage, and build scripts
configure done.
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var clm_demand with val flanduse_timeseries 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var clm_start_type with val startup 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var model_year_align_ndep with val
1850 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var rcp with val 6 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var sim_year with val 1850 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var sim_year_range with val
1850-2100 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var stream_year_first_ndep with val
1850 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var stream_year_last_ndep with val
2100 
adding use_case 1850-2100_rcp6_transient defaults for var use_case_desc with val Simulate
transient land-use, aerosol and Nitrogen deposition changes with historical data from
1850 to 2005 and then with the RCP6 scenario from AIM
 
build-namelist - No default value found for flanduse_timeseries.
            Are defaults provided for this resolution and land mask?
ERROR: generate_resolved.csh error for lnd template
configure error: configure generated error in attempting to created resolved scripts
</screen>
</example>
The important thing to note here is the line:
<screen width="99">
ERROR: generate_resolved.csh error for lnd template
</screen>
which tells us that the problem is in the land template. It may also indicate problems
in one of the other templates (atm, ccsm, cpl, glc, ice, or ocn), in which case you 
should consult the appropriate model user's guide, and examine the given template file
in <filename>Tools/Templates</filename>. For more information on working with template
files see <xref linkend="editing_templates"></xref>.
</para>
<para>
In the example above, it's obvious that the problem is coming from the &clm; &buildnml;,
in other situations it might not be so obvious where the problem is occurring. In such
cases it might be useful to add a "set echo" command to the top of the template file so
that each command in the template will be echoed to the screen and you can see what 
is happening and where the error is occurring.
<screen width="99">
set echo
</screen>
</para>
<para>
In the example, the error is that the &clm; XML database does NOT have a
<filename>flanduse_timeseries</filename> for the given resolution, rcp scenario and ocean mask. 
That means you will need to create the file and then supply the file into your case. See
<xref linkend="tools"></xref> for more information on creating files, and see
<xref linkend="adding_files"></xref> for more information on adding files to the 
XML database. Alternatively, you can provide the file to your case by creating
a user namelist as shown in <xref linkend="config_time_nml"></xref>.
</para>
<note>
<para>
The two most common problems from your &clm; template will be errors from the &clm;
&configure; or &buildnml;. For more information on these scripts see:
<xref linkend="clm_configure_script"></xref> and 
<link linkend="CLMBLDNML">the section on &CLMBLDNML;</link>.
</para>
</note>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="trouble_w_building">
<title>Trouble with Building</title>
<para>
Here's an example of running the build for a case and having it fail in the land model
build. As you can see it lists which model component is being built and the build log
for that component.
<screen width="99">
 CCSM BUILDEXE SCRIPT STARTING
 - Build Libraries: mct pio csm_share 
Sat Jun 19 21:21:19 MDT 2010 /ptmp/erik/test_build/mct/mct.bldlog.100619-212107
Sat Jun 19 21:22:18 MDT 2010 /ptmp/erik/test_build/pio/pio.bldlog.100619-212107
Sat Jun 19 21:23:18 MDT 2010
/ptmp/erik/test_build/csm_share/csm_share.bldlog.100619-212107
Sat Jun 19 21:24:00 MDT 2010 /ptmp/erik/test_build/run/cpl.bldlog.100619-212107
Sat Jun 19 21:24:00 MDT 2010 /ptmp/erik/test_build/run/atm.bldlog.100619-212107
Sat Jun 19 21:24:06 MDT 2010 /ptmp/erik/test_build/run/lnd.bldlog.100619-212107
ERROR: clm.buildexe.csh failed, see /ptmp/erik/test_build/run/lnd.bldlog.100619-212107
ERROR: cat /ptmp/erik/test_build/run/lnd.bldlog.100619-212107
</screen>
You can then examine the build log that failed and see what went wrong. Most compilers
will give the full filepath and line number for the file that filed to compile.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="trouble_w_running">
<title>Trouble with Running</title>
<para>
Tracking down problems while the model is running is much more difficult to do
than configure or build problems. In this section we will give some suggestions
on how to find run time problems. Below we show the log file results of a job
that aborted while running.
<screen width="99">
 CCSM PRESTAGE SCRIPT HAS FINISHED SUCCESSFULLY
Sun Jun 20 18:24:06 MDT 2010 -- CSM EXECUTION BEGINS HERE
Sun Jun 20 18:24:35 MDT 2010 -- CSM EXECUTION HAS FINISHED
Model did not complete - see /ptmp/erik/test_run/run/cpl.log.100620-182358
</screen>
In the next section we will talk about using the different log files to track
down problems, and find out where the problem is coming from. In the section
after that we give some general advice on debugging problems and some suggestions
on ideas that may be helpful to track the problem down. Some of the examples
below are from the &KnownBugs; file.
</para>
<sect2 id="querying_log_files">
<title>Tracking Problems by Querying Log Files</title>
<para>
The first thing to do when tracking down problems is to query the different log
files to see if you can discover where the problem occurs, and any error messages about
it. It's important to figure out if the problem comes in at initialization or in the
run phase of the model, and in which model component the problem happens. There
are different log files for the different major components, and they all end 
with the date and time in YYMMDD-HHMMSS format (2-digit: year, month, day, hour
minute and second). When the model runs to completion the log files will be copied
to the <filename>logs</filename> directory in the script directory, but when the
model fails they will remain in the run directory. Here's an example list of
log files from an "I" case where the model dies in the land model initialization.
For "I" cases the sea-ice and ocean components are just stubs and don't create
log files (and unless running with the active land-ice model "glc" log files won't
be created either).
<screen width="99">
atm.log.100620-182358
ccsm.log.100620-182358
cpl.log.100620-182358
lnd.log.100620-182358
</screen>
</para>

<sect3 id="cpl_log">
<title>The coupler log file</title>
<para>
The first log file to check is the coupler log file so that you can see where
the model dies and which model component it fails in. When the model dies at
initialization the last model component listed is the component that failed.
</para>
<para>
Example of a case that fails in the &clm; land model initialization.
<screen width="99">
(seq_timemgr_clockPrint)     Prev Time   = 00001201   00000
(seq_timemgr_clockPrint)     Next Time   = 99991201   00000
(seq_timemgr_clockPrint)     Intervl yms =     9999       0           0

(seq_mct_drv) : Initialize each component: atm, lnd, ocn, and ice
(seq_mct_drv) : Initialize atm component
(seq_mct_drv) : Initialize lnd component
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ccsm_log">
<title>The ccsm log file</title>
<para>
The ccsm log files are to some extent the "garbage collection" of log output. The
&clm; sends it's output from it's master processor, but sends other output and possibly
errors to the ccsm log file. Because, of this, often error messages are somewhere in the
ccsm log file. However, since there is so much other output it may be difficult to find.
For example, here is some output from an older version of &cesm; (&cesm102;) where the 
RTM river routing file (before it was converted to &netcdf;) was not provided and
the error on the open statement for the file was embedded near the end of the ccsm log
file.
<screen width="99">
NODE#  NAME
(    0)  be1105en.ucar.edu
"/gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/lnd/clm/src/riverroute/RtmMod.F90", line
239: 1525-155 The file name provided in the OPEN statement for unit 1 has zero length or
contains all blanks.  The program will recover by ignoring the OPEN statement.
"/gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/lnd/clm/src/riverroute/RtmMod.F90", line
241: 1525-001 The READ statement on the file fort.1 cannot be completed because the end
of the file was reached.  The program will stop.

Running: ./ccsm.exe 
Please wait...

Memory usage for   ./ccsm.exe (task #   0) is:      51696 KB. Exit status: 1. Signal: 0
</screen>
Although the example is from an earlier version of the model it still serves to
illustrate finding problems from the ccsm log file.
</para>
<para>
When working with the ccsm log file, for a run-time problem, you will need to be able 
to separate it's output into three categories: pre-crash, crash, and post-crash. The
pre-crash section is everything that is normal output for good operation of the model.
The crash section is the section where the model dies and reports on the actual problem.
the post-crash section is the cleanup and finalization after the model dies. The most
important part of this of course is the crash section. The tricky part is distinguishing
it from the other sections. Also because the ccsm log file most likely has duplicated
output from multiple processors it is even more difficult to distinguish the different
sections and to some extent the sections may be intertwined, as different processors 
reach the different sections at different times. Because, of this reducing the number of
processors for your simulation may help you sort out the output in the file (see
<xref linkend="fewer_pes"></xref>). Also much of the output from the ccsm log file are
system level information having to do with &mpi; multiprocessing. Usually you can ignore
this information, but it makes it more difficult to trudge through.
</para>
<para>
Sometimes the ccsm log file is the ONLY file available, because the model terminates
early in initialization. In this case understanding the output in the ccsm log file
becomes even more important. This also indicates the model did NOT advance far enough
to reach the initialization of the individual model components. This may mean that the
initialization of the multiprocessing for &mpi; and/or &omp; failed, or that the
reading of the driver namelist file "drv_in" failed.
</para>
<para>
Here we show those three sections for a ccsm log file where a two task job failed on
reading the namelist file. For a typical job with many tasks similar sections of this
will be repeated not just twice but for each task and hence make it harder to read.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Pre-crash section of the ccsm log file</emphasis>
<screen width="99">
ATTENTION: 0031-386  MP_INSTANCES setting ignored when LoadLeveler is not being used.
ATTENTION: 0031-386  MP_INSTANCES setting ignored when LoadLeveler is not being used.
ATTENTION: 0031-378 MP_EUIDEVICE setting ignored when LoadLeveler is not being used.  
ATTENTION: 0031-386  MP_INSTANCES setting ignored when LoadLeveler is not being used.
   0:INFO: 0031-724  Executing program: &lt;/usr/local/lsf/7.0/aix5-64/bin/lsnrt_run&gt;
   1:INFO: 0031-724  Executing program: &lt;/usr/local/lsf/7.0/aix5-64/bin/lsnrt_run&gt;
   0:/contrib/bin/ccsm_launch: process 401894 bound to logical CPU 0 on host be0310en.ucar.edu ...
   1:/contrib/bin/ccsm_launch: process 439264 bound to logical CPU 1 on host be0310en.ucar.edu ...
   0:INFO: 0031-619  64bit(us, Packet striping on)  ppe_rmas MPCI_MSG: MPI/MPCI library was compiled on   Wed Aug  5 13:36:06 2009
   0: 
   1:LAPI version #14.26 2008/11/23 11:02:30 1.296 src/rsct/lapi/lapi.c, lapi, rsct_rpt53, rpt53s004a 09/04/29 64bit(us)  library compiled on Wed Apr 29 15:30:42 2009
   1:.
   1:LAPI is using lightweight lock.
   0:LAPI version #14.26 2008/11/23 11:02:30 1.296 src/rsct/lapi/lapi.c, lapi, rsct_rpt53, rpt53s004a 09/04/29 64bit(us)  library compiled on Wed Apr 29 15:30:42 2009
   0:.
   0:LAPI is using lightweight lock.
   0:Use health ping for failover/recovery
   1:Use health ping for failover/recovery
   0:Initial communication over instance 2.
   1:Initial communication over instance 0.
   1:IB RDMA initialization completed successfully
   1:The MPI shared memory protocol is used for the job
   0:IB RDMA initialization completed successfully
   0:LAPI job ID for this job is: 1684890719
   0:The MPI shared memory protocol is used for the job
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  7 GLOBAL ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  2   ATM  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  1   LND  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  4   ICE  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  5   GLC  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  3   OCN  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_setcomm)  initialize ID (  6   CPL  ) pelist   =     0     1     1 ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_joincomm) initialize ID (  8 CPLATM ) join IDs =     6     2       ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_joincomm) initialize ID (  9 CPLLND ) join IDs =     6     1       ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_joincomm) initialize ID ( 10 CPLICE ) join IDs =     6     4       ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_joincomm) initialize ID ( 11 CPLOCN ) join IDs =     6     3       ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:(seq_comm_joincomm) initialize ID ( 12 CPLGLC ) join IDs =     6     5       ( npes =     2) ( nthreads =  1)
   0:  
   0: (seq_comm_printcomms) ID layout : global pes vs local pe for each ID
   0:     gpe        LND      ATM      OCN      ICE      GLC      CPL    GLOBAL   CPLATM   CPLLND   CPLICE   CPLOCN   CPLGLC    nthrds
   0:     ---      ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------   ------    ------
   0:       0   :       0        0        0        0        0        0        0        0        0        0        0        0        1
   1:       1   :       1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1        1
   1:  
   0: (t_initf) Read in prof_inparm namelist from: drv_in
   1: (seq_io_init) cpl_io_stride, iotasks or root out of bounds - resetting to defaults  4 0 1
   0: piolib_mod.f90 1353 1 2 1 2
   1: piolib_mod.f90 1353 1 2 1 2
   0: pio_support::pio_die:: myrank= 0 : ERROR: piolib_mod.f90: 1354 : not enough procs for the stride
   1: pio_support::pio_die:: myrank= 1 : ERROR: piolib_mod.f90: 1354 : not enough procs for the stride
</screen>
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Crash section of the ccsm log file</emphasis>
<screen width="99">
   0:
   0:  Traceback:
   1:
   1:  Traceback:
   0:    Offset 0x00000c4c in procedure __pio_support_NMOD_piodie, near line 88 in file pio_support.F90.in
   1:    Offset 0x00000c4c in procedure __pio_support_NMOD_piodie, near line 88 in file pio_support.F90.in
   0:    Offset 0x00000fd0 in procedure __piolib_mod_NMOD_init, near line 1354 in file piolib_mod.F90
   1:    Offset 0x00000fd0 in procedure __piolib_mod_NMOD_init, near line 1354 in file piolib_mod.F90
   1:    Offset 0x00000398 in procedure __seq_io_mod_NMOD_seq_io_init, near line 247 in file /gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/drv/shr/seq_io_mod.F90
   0:    Offset 0x00000398 in procedure __seq_io_mod_NMOD_seq_io_init, near line 247 in file /gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/drv/shr/seq_io_mod.F90
   0:    Offset 0x0001aa88 in procedure ccsm_driver, near line 465 in file /gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/drv/driver/ccsm_driver.F90
   0:    --- End of call chain ---
   1:    Offset 0x0001aa88 in procedure ccsm_driver, near line 465 in file /gpfs/proj2/fis/cgd/home/erik/clm_trunk/models/drv/driver/ccsm_driver.F90
   1:    --- End of call chain ---
</screen>
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Post-crash section of the ccsm log file</emphasis>
<screen width="99">
   1:Communication statistics of task 1 is associated with task key: 1684890719_1
   0:Communication statistics of task 0 is associated with task key: 1684890719_0
   0:
   0:Running: ./ccsm.exe 
   0:Please wait...
   0:
   0:Memory usage for   ./ccsm.exe (task #   0) is:     198892 KB. Exit status: 134. Signal: 0
   1:
   1:Running: ./ccsm.exe 
   1:Please wait...
   1:
   1:Memory usage for   ./ccsm.exe (task #   0) is:     198572 KB. Exit status: 134. Signal: 0
INFO: 0031-656  I/O file STDOUT closed by task 0
INFO: 0031-656  I/O file STDERR closed by task 0
ERROR: 0031-250  task 0: IOT/Abort trap
INFO: 0031-656  I/O file STDOUT closed by task 1
INFO: 0031-656  I/O file STDERR closed by task 1
ERROR: 0031-250  task 1: IOT/Abort trap
INFO: 0031-639  Exit status from pm_respond = 0
ATTENTION: 0031-386  MP_INSTANCES setting ignored when LoadLeveler is not being used.
Job  /usr/local/lsf/7.0/aix5-64/bin/poejob /contrib/bin/ccsm_launch /contrib/bin/job_memusage.exe ./ccsm.exe

TID   HOST_NAME   COMMAND_LINE            STATUS            TERMINATION_TIME
===== ========== ================  =======================  ===================
00000 be0310en   /contrib/bin/ccs  Exit (134)               08/31/2010 12:32:57
00001 be0310en   /contrib/bin/ccs  Exit (134)               08/31/2010 12:32:57
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="clm_log">
<title>The &clm; log file</title>
<para>
Of course when you are working with and making changes to &clm;, most of your focus
will be on the &clm; log file and the errors it shows. As already pointed out 
if you don't see errors in the <filename>lnd.log.*</filename> file you should look
in the <filename>ccsm.log.*</filename> to see if any errors showed up there.
</para>
<para>
Here's an example of the <filename>lnd.log.*</filename> file when running 
&PTSMODE; with initial conditions (this is bug 1025 in the &KnownBugs; file).
<screen width="99">
 Successfully initialized variables for accumulation
 
 reading restart file I2000CN_f09_g16_c100503.clm2.r.0001-01-01-00000.nc                                                                                                                                                                                                              
 Reading restart dataset
 ERROR - setlatlon.F:Cant get variable dim for lat or lsmlat
 ENDRUN: called without a message string
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="datm_log">
<title>The &datm; log file</title>
<para>
When working with "I cases" the second most common problems after &clm; problems are
problems with the data atmosphere model. So examining the <filename>atm.log.*</filename>
is important.
</para>
<para>
Here's an example of a problem that occurs when the wrong prescribed aerosol file
is given to a <literal>pt1_pt1</literal> simulation.
<screen width="99">
(datm_comp_init)  atm mode = CLMNCEP
(shr_strdata_init)  calling shr_dmodel_mapSet for fill
(shr_strdata_init)  calling shr_dmodel_mapSet for remap
 ('shr_map_getWts') ERROR: yd outside bounds  19.5000000000000000
(shr_sys_abort) ERROR: ('shr_map_getWts')  ERROR yd outside 90 degree bounds
(shr_sys_abort) WARNING: calling shr_mpi_abort() and stopping
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="batch_log">
<title>The batch log files</title>
<para>
The names of the batch log files will depend on the batch system of the machine
that is being used. They will normally be in the script directory. Usually, they
don't contain important information, but they are a last resort place to look for
error messages. On the &ncar; IBM system "bluefire" the batch files are called
with names that start with "poe" and then either "stderr" or "stdout", with the
job number at the end.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="gen_adv_dbg_runtime">
<title>General Advice on Debugging Run time Problems</title>
<para>
Here are some suggestions on how to track down a problem while running. In general
if the problem still occurs for a simpler case, it will be easier to track down.
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run in DEBUG mode</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run with a smaller set of processors</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run in serial mode with a single processor</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run at a lower resolution</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run a simpler case</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Run with a debugger</emphasis></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<sect3 id="debug_mode">
<title>Run in DEBUG mode</title>
<para>
The first thing to try is to run in DEBUG mode so that float point trapping will be 
triggered as well as array bounds checking and other things the compiler can turn
on to help you find problems. To do this edit the &envbuild; file and set <envar>DEBUG
</envar> to <literal>TRUE</literal> as follows:
<screen width="99">
> ./xmlchange -file env_build.xml -id DEBUG -val TRUE
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="fewer_pes">
<title>Run with a smaller set of processors</title>
<para>
Another way to simplify the system is to run with a smaller set of processors. You
will need to clean the configure and edit the <filename>env_mach_pes.xml</filename>.
For example, to run with four processors:
<screen width="99">
> ./configure -cleanall
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_ATM -val 4
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_LND -val 4
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_ICE -val 4
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_OCN -val 4
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_CPL -val 4
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_GLC -val 4
> ./configure -case
</screen>
Another recommended simplification is to run without threading, so set the
<envar>NTHRDS</envar> for each component to "1" if it isn't already. Sometimes,
multiprocessing problems require a certain number of processors before they occur
so you may not be able to debug the problem without enough processors. But, it's always
good to reduce it to as low a number as possible to make it simpler. For threading
problems you may have to have threading enabled to find the problem, but you can run
with 1, 2, or 3 threads to see what happens.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="run_serially">
<title>Run in serial mode with a single processor</title>
<para>
Simplifying to one processor removes all multi-processing problems and makes
the case as simple as possible. If you can enable <envar>USE_MPI_SERIAL</envar>
you will also be able to run interactively rather than having to submit to a job
queue, which sometimes makes it easier to run and debug. If you can use 
<envar>USE_MPI_SERIAL</envar> you can also use threading, but still run interactively
in order to use more processors to make it faster if needed.
<screen width="99">
> ./configure -cleanall
# Set tasks and threads for each component to 1
# You could also set threads to something &gt; 1 for speed, but still
# run interactively if threading isn't an issue.
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_ATM -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_ATM -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_LND -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_LND -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_ICE -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_ICE -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_OCN -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_OCN -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_CPL -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_CPL -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTASKS_GLC -val 1
> ./xmlchange -file env_mach_pes.xml -id NTHRDS_GLC -val 1
# If mpi-serial capability is available on the machine you are using
# set USE_MPI_SERIAL to true so that you can run interactively
> ./xmlchange -file env_conf.xml -id USE_MPI_SERIAL -val TRUE
> ./configure -case
# Then build your case
# And finally run, by running the *.run script interactively
# (If you were able to set USE_MPI_SERIAL to true)
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="lower_res">
<title>Run at a lower resolution</title>
<para>
If you can create a new case running at a lower resolution and replicate the problem
it may be easier to solve. This of course requires creating a whole new case, and trying
out different lower resolutions.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="simpler_case">
<title>Run a simpler case</title>
<para>
Along the same lines, you might try running a simpler case, trying another compset
with a simpler setup and see if you can replicate the problem and then debug from that 
simpler case. Again, of course you will need to create new cases to do this.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="dbx">
<title>Run with a debugger</title>
<para>
Another suggestion is to run the model with a debugger such as: <command>dbx</command>,
<command>gdb</command>, or <command>totalview</command>. Often to run with a debugger
you will need to reduce the number of processors as outlined above. Some debuggers such
as <command>dbx</command> will only work with one processor, while more advanced
debuggers such as <command>totalview</command> can work with both &mpi; tasks and OMP
threads. Even simple debuggers though can be used to query core files, to see where
the code was at when it died (for example using the <command>where</command> in 
<command>dbx</command> for a core file can be very helpful. For help in running
with a debugger you will need to contact your system administrators for the machine
you are running on.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>
</chapter>
<!-- End of special cases chapter-->
